<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of Nicholas Smith against a reply to his discussion of some pointes taught by Mr. Doctour Kellison in his Treatise of the ecclesiasticall hierarchy. By A.B.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115849</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851066</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851066</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00166)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:10,)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of Nicholas Smith against a reply to his discussion of some pointes taught by Mr. Doctour Kellison in his Treatise of the ecclesiasticall hierarchy. By A.B.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
                  <author>Wilson, M., attributed author.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 82, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Nicolas Courant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Rouen :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by STC to M. Wilson.</note>
                  <note>Date altered on title page to read 1630.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Knott, Edward, 1582-1656. --  Modest briefe discussion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kellison, Matthew. --  Treatise of the hierarchie and divers orders of the church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF NICHOLAS SMITH AGAINST A REPLY TO HIS DISCVSSION OF SOME pointes taught by <hi>Mr. Doctour Kelliſon</hi> in his Treatiſe of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By A. B.</p>
            <q>We dare not match or compare our ſelues with certayne, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commend them ſelues. But we meaſure our ſelues in our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, and compare our ſelues to our ſelues. But we will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory aboue our meaſure, but according to the meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Rule, which God hath meaſured to vs; a meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to reach vnto you, do we extend our ſelues beyonde. For w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are come as farre, as to you in the Ghoſpell of Chriſt. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Corinth: 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>At Roüen by NICOLAS COVRANT. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</p>
            <p>MAISTER Doctour <hi>Kelliſon</hi> wrote a Booke intituled, <hi>A Treatiſe of the Ecceſiaſticall Hierarchy,</hi> wherein among other points, he chiefly intended to proue, that Engliſh Catholikes could not in conſcience refuſe a Biſhop, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, by his comming, their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were to be increaſed.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe of <hi>M. Doctour</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by <hi>A modest Diſcuſsion;</hi> againſt which was ſet forth in Print, a litle Booke with title of <hi>An Inquiſition</hi> &amp;c. of which ſome Copies, euen in print, haue
<pb facs="tcp:16320:3"/>that falſe ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der about the <hi>Pouder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (which Copies were ſpread abroad both in the North, &amp; South of <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</hi>) Others haue it not.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Inqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> was preſently confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a <hi>Charitable Qualificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> to which was adioyned an <hi>Admonition to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> The Author whereof had not, at that tyme, ſeene in Print, any of thoſe Copies, which mentioned the forſayd ſlaunderous poynt; which I thought good heere to note, for thy knowledge.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> there is newly come forth a ſecond anſwere to the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſsion,</hi> called, <hi>A Reply to Nicolas Smith his Diſcuſsion &amp;c.</hi> To this <hi>Reply,</hi> I now anſwere, in defence of <hi>Nicolas Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou mayſt perhaps wonder, that the <hi>Reply</hi> (which if we haue an eye to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fference of print, in bulke is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>M. Doctours Hierarchy</hi>) ſhould be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſo few leaues of paper. And I muſt confeſſe, I did not at firſt hope, to haue ended the <hi>Defence,</hi> in ſo few, eyther <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> or <hi>daies,</hi> which were but <hi>ſeauen,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to the <hi>ſeauen</hi> Queſtions ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Replyer:</hi> within which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:16320:3"/>of tyme, I was confined both to reade, and anſwere the <hi>Reply:</hi> and yet in all ſincerity I do auouch, not to haue omitted the anſwere of any one thing, wherein I conceaued there myght be the leaſt apparence of difficulty. The reaſon of this breuity was double.</p>
            <p>The one, becauſe many chiefe obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> were afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand fully anſwered by the <hi>Qualification</hi> before the <hi>Reply</hi> came out; to which therfore it will be ſufficient to referre thee in ſuch points. Beſides, there is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed a learned &amp; elegant booke, with Title of <hi>An Apology of the holy Sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoliques proceeding, for the gouernment of the Catholikes of England, during the tyme of Perſecution,</hi> which may not only ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to anſwere the <hi>Reply,</hi> but it alone in lieu of al others, were ſufficient to ſhew the manifold deficiency of <hi>M. Doctours</hi> Treatiſe, with, I can hardely ſay whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy more pleaſure, or profit.</p>
            <p>The other reaſon was, becauſe the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> taketh all occaſions, to dilate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in diuers points, which eyther are vulgarly knowne in Schooles, or were
<pb facs="tcp:16320:4"/>neuer denyed by <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> or may be equally ſpoken by both parts, or els are anſwered, by the only peruſall of the <hi>Diſcuſsion</hi> it ſelfe; which I earneſtly intreat thee to reuiew, if thou fynd any thing obiected by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> which may ſeeme to haue difficulty; and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, the only reading will ſerue for anſwere. Which to be true, I found by my owne experience; in ſo much, as for anſwering the Reply, I did in truth vſe no booke, beſides the <hi>Hierarchy, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſsion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Qualification,</hi> although I could not doubt, but that the examination of diuers Authors cited by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> would haue adminiſtred no ſmall adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt him.</p>
            <p>I verily belieue, if thou read the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> with indifferency, and attention, thou wilt perceaue, that he rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> then <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> whoſe wordes he is forced to excuſe, by the common Rule of Charity, that in them he had a good meaninge; but in the cheifeſt poynts of ſubſtance, at length he commeth to ioyne with the <hi>Diſcuſſour.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:4"/>
            <p>Diuers things of moment, he wholy omitteth without anſwering, or mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them. Vpon the whole matter, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, this iudgement may be giuen, of the quantity, &amp; quality of this worke in general; That he hath taken great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to procure, that few will haue pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to reade ouer his whole Booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Drs.</hi> modeſty is by him much extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, &amp; <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſore blamed, for the contrary. Indeed he that without cauſe giueth the firſt ſtroake, as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> did, hath no great reaſon to be angry with the party, that beareth the blow. And whatſoeuer the <hi>Replyer</hi> ſayth in his <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> adioyned by his Reply, <hi>Nicolas Smiths Diſcuſsion</hi> will be proued to be truly modeſt, if the paſſages be read as they lye in the <hi>Diſcuſsion,</hi> &amp; not as they are lamely cited by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> as I could ſhew in euery particular, if I had not reſolued to be very briefe.</p>
            <p>It is ordinary with the <hi>Replyer,</hi> to blame <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> as if he had accuſed <hi>M. Doctour</hi> of ſome doctrins which <hi>Nic-Smith</hi> layd not to his charge, but only ſhewed, that out of his <hi>Tenets,</hi> certayne
<pb facs="tcp:16320:5"/>Concluſions would follow, which ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor any other could defend; but he did not ſay, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, or intended ſuch Concluſions.</p>
            <p>In this manner <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> tearmed a certayne Argument, a Doughty one, which yet he did not affirme, to be <hi>M. Doctours</hi> argument, but only that out of S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> wordes, rightly vnderſtood, no better Argument could be drawne in fauour of <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> who out of the ſame words, framed an argument, quite different from that, which <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> tearmed <hi>doughty,</hi> as may be ſeene in the <hi>Diſcuſsion q.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p>The like I could ſhew, in all the reſt, but content my ſelfe with requeſting thee, vnpartiall Reader, ſtill to ſuſpend thy iudgment, till, in particulars, thou haſt ſeene the words, and connexion of <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Replyer</hi> himſelfe, is farre from <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> his modeſty. Scarcely he giueth any one anſwere, not accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed with ſome taunt; So that, to ſet downe all his ſharpe ſpeaches, were but to re-coppy the Booke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:5"/>
            <p>Within the compaſſe of two <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions,</hi> he hath theſe charitable ſayings: <hi>He fauoureth Heretikes. pag.</hi> 26. <hi>Behould</hi> Nicolas Smith <hi>his little ſubtility. pag.</hi> 31. <hi>Which is no leſſe then a falſe calumniation. pag.</hi> 32. <hi>I pitty</hi> M. Nicolas Smith <hi>his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, and the neceſsity he is driuen to, which</hi> cogit ad turpia. <hi>pag.</hi> 43. Nicolas Smith <hi>ioyneth with heretikes in this poynt pag.</hi> 96. And the ſame agayne <hi>pag.</hi> 110. <hi>What Deuine, yea Cathecumen, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Cathechiſme, would haue giuen ſuch an anſwere? pag.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>He fauoureth Caluin. pag.</hi> 111. And in the ſame page, <hi>I cannot tell how heerafter he can looke them in the face:</hi> although in this he haue reaſon, for he ſpake of ſome Ieſuites, who dyed longe ſince, and it would be hard for the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> to looke them in the face, if he be yet liuinge, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> will haue him, in his Preface to the Reader: where alſo <hi>pag.</hi> 16. he ſayth, <hi>That the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſour ſeemeth to shew litle of the ſpirit of a Religious man:</hi> for which, if it be true, the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> I graunt, ought to be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and endeauour to correſpond bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his vocation. Howſoeuer, I dare
<pb facs="tcp:16320:6"/>ſay for <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> that, if he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, he would hartily thank the <hi>Replyer,</hi> for the occaſion he affoardeth him of merit, and ſo do I, in his behalfe; wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, that as we are all <hi>domestici fidei,</hi> ſo we may be <hi>charitatis,</hi> of one <hi>beliefe,</hi> and <hi>heart.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:6"/>
            <head>The Queſtions handled.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>VVHat iudgment may be framed of</hi> M Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours <hi>Treatiſe in generall.</hi> pag 1.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>VVhether without a Bishop, there can be a particular Church?</hi> pag. 5.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>VVhether by the diuine Law, euery particular Church, muſt haue its Bishop?</hi> pag. 19.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>VVhether a Countrey, although the Perſecution should be increaſed, by occaſion of hauing a Bishop, could refuſe one, if it were only for the Sacrament of Confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> pag. 38.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Concerning</hi> M. Doctours <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, betweene Bishops, inferiour Paſtours, &amp; Religious men.</hi> pa. 53.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:16320:7"/>
               <item>6. <hi>VVhether Religious, as Religious, be of the Hierarchy?</hi> pag. 68.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>VVhether by the precedent Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we haue ſufficiently anſwered</hi> M. Doctours <hi>Treatiſe, for ſuch points, as eyther deſerued Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or required Explication.</hi> pag. 75.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="approbations">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:7"/>
            <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
            <div type="approbation">
               <p>LIbellum hunc Anglico idiomate conſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum &amp; inſcriptum, <hi>A Defence of Nicolas Smith, against A Reply to his Diſcuſſion:</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentè &amp; accuratè perlegi, &amp; diligenter &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turè examinaui, &amp; inuenio non ſolum ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni nota, quantum ad doctrinam Fidei Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae morumue proborum immunem: verum etiam afflictae Patriae noſtrae valde vtilem, &amp; ad conſcientias Catholicorum in eâdem ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandas ferè neceſſarium. Tractantur enim in co breuiter, ſolidè tamen &amp; modeſté, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiones nonnullae graues &amp; difficiles, ex qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum veridicâ ſolutione conſtabit Catholicis, non imminere illis tantam in multis cauſis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligationem, tantumue onus conſcientiae, quantum nonnulli auctores editis ſuis libris, imponere nituntur ex leuibus fundamentis. Quod eo magis in hoc Scriptore laud and um eſt, quo omnia, quae dicit &amp; docet, ſunt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formia communiori magiſue receptae Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum Claſſicorum auctoritati; quinimo &amp; recentibus decretis ac reſponſis à Sede A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolica inſinuatis. Quapropter cenſeo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino dignum &amp; iuſtum, vt hic liber, permiſſu tamen Superiorum, praelo mandetur. Datum Duaci in Conuentu noſtro Sancti Gregorij Magni, 10. die Ianuarij. 1631.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>F. Rudeſindus Barlo S. Theol. Doctor, &amp; Profeſsor in Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitate Duacenâ.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="approbation">
               <pb facs="tcp:16320:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>ATtentè legimus Anglicum hoc Scriptum, cuint titulus est,</hi> A Defence of Nicolas Smith agaynſt A Reply to his Diſcuſſion, of ſome poynts taught by M. Doctour Kelliſon in his Treatiſe of the Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy. <hi>In quo nec Catholicam Fidem, nec bonos mores vllatenus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di, ſed ſuſceptam Defenſionem, cum plenâ antedicta Replicae ſatisfactione, praestitam inuenimus. Datum Louany</hi> 16. <hi>Ianuarij</hi> 1631.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>Fr. Robertus Chamberlinus S. Theol. Lector in Collegio Fratrum Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Louanienſium.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fr. Malachias Fallon S. Theol. Lector.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="approbation">
               <p>QVandoquidem à ſupranominatis doctis viris, &amp; linguam Anglicanam callenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus liber hic citatus probatus eſt, per me quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que licet vt imprimatur. Actum Tornaci Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiorum 22. Ianuarij 1631.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ioannes Boucher S. Theol. Doctor Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus, nec non Cathedralis Eccleſia Tornacenſis Canonicus, Archidiaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, &amp; Librorum Cenſor.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="question">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:8"/>
            <head>THE I. QVESTION <hi>What Judgment may be framed of</hi> M. Doctours <hi>Treatiſe in generall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Replyer</hi> thinkes he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> in a contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for affirming <hi>M. Doctour</hi> to haue been the firſt that put in print <hi>A Treatiſe of the Hierarchy,</hi> in the Engliſh tongue, and yet confeſſeth that diuers before him handled this argument, both in Latin and vulgar la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guages. But it is cleere the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of ſuch a Treatiſe concerning the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> put in print, intended, proſecuted, appropriated to England, for proofe of the obligation Catholiques haue to receaue a Biſhop, and ſuch like purpoſes peculiar to our Country. This <hi>M. Doctour</hi> hath done, and hath done it the firſt of any in theſe dayes. Would to God he had not. The law of Nature pleadeth for the right men haue to defend themſelues from aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but doth not warrant him that vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked offendeth his neighbour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If writing of Bookes in this kind be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16320:9"/>of ſmall Comfort to Catholiques, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience muſt be aſcribed to him alone who gaue the firſt blow, and impoſed vpon the partyes aggrieued, a neceſſity of iuſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. To cure a wound giuen at once to a number of worthy perſons, is but a bounden duty, and an obliged acte of common cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. This did other Regulars; this I doe at this preſent, and noe more. <hi>M. Doctour</hi> and his Second, obliged vs to ſome anſwer; I will tye my ſelfe to doe it with moderation. Likwiſe <hi>Suarcz, Platus,</hi> and others haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the calling of ſecular, and ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men, but not by way of application to particular circumſtances of any perſons, places, or controuerſies. <hi>M. Doctours</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to charity is not by the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Verball,</hi> as though it came not from the heart, which the <hi>Replyer</hi> obiecteth <hi>n.</hi> 7. (for he only is to erect a Tribunall of ſearch into mans heart who made it,) but becauſe while in wordes he perſuadeth to charity, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then in deedes by the writing of this booke he did mightily preiudice Charity, as by too much experience we find, and was eaſy to be forſeene.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> neuer accuſeth <hi>M. Doctour</hi> abſolutely of want of Logike, or Prudence, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> auerreth <hi>n.</hi> 12. He ſayth that in this Treatiſe, to proue the neceſſity of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in England, <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſerueth himſelfe of Principles more hard then the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is agaynſt the rules of Logike. This may argue him to defend a bad cauſe, not vniuerſally to want Logike. What the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16320:9"/>
               <hi>Replyer</hi> hath <hi>n.</hi> 19. is alſo obiected by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> and anſwered by the <hi>Qualificatour Sect. 6. n. 19.</hi> ſhewing that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> is not taxed for prouing his Concluſions by Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or Effectes &amp;c. but becauſe he aſſumeth Principles more vncertayne, and leſſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable then the Concluſion, as in the ſayd place is demonſtrated. I belieue it would be an hard taske for any man to proue, That for the onely vndoubtedneſſe, or greater aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſſe of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> Catholiques are obliged to haue a Biſhop, although we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that by his comming their preſſures were to be aggrauated with new increaſe of perſecution. For why ſhould this affliction be, of neceſſity, added to the already afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Becauſe (forfooth) ſome very few Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours haue taught that <hi>Confirmation</hi> cannot be adminiſtred by a Prieſt, with ſpeciall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Pope, although the whole ſtreame of Deuines runne to the contrary ſide, with <hi>S. Thomas;</hi> and ſome hold, that ſince the Councell of <hi>Florence</hi> the other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion meriteth Cenſure. This poynt is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently handled in the <hi>Qualification.</hi> Heere I add this inſtance. Some few Deuines are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of opinion, that the Prieſt is Miniſter of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> without whome, according to theſe Authors, it is only a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Contract, not a Sacrament; wil therfore the <hi>Replyer</hi> ſay, that Engliſh Catholickes are obliged to receaue Prieſts, with increaſe of perſecution, if it were only for to haue the <hi>vndoubted</hi> Sacrament of <hi>Matrimony?</hi> And yet if the matter be duly conſidered, perhaps
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16320:10"/>one may truly affirme, that as great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences, and ſinnes of enmity, iniuſtice, incontinency &amp;c. are like to be dayly, and hourely incurred, for want of grace, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the Sacrament of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> as in another kind for want of Confirmation, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a perſecuted Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try. If thoſe Deuines who teach, that the Prieſt is the Miniſter of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> had taught that a Biſhop were the neceſſary Miniſter of the ſame Sacrament, the <hi>Replyer</hi> would perhaps alledge them for the neceſſity of a Biſhop although with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of perſecution.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The chiefeſt point of doctrine in this Queſtion, or rather the point which entreth into all the enſuing Queſtions, is touched by the <hi>Diſcuſſour n.</hi> 15. and by the <hi>Replyer</hi> left without anſwere. It was: That <hi>M. Doctours</hi> arguments for the neceſſity of a Biſhop in England, proue more then himſelfe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or can auouch. For the inſtitution, and commaund of our Sauiour, that his Church ſhould be gouerned by Biſhops, concerneth ſuch Biſhops, as are properly <hi>Ordinaryes, Princes,</hi> &amp; Biſhops of <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> not by <hi>Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, Deputation,</hi> or <hi>Ordinaryes in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner,</hi> which is not of Diuiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and is the moſt that my Lord of <hi>Calcedon</hi> doth challeng. If the diuine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtution, and commaund, were fulfilled by Ordinaryes, in an Extraordinary manner, the Pope might gouerne the whole Church by ſuch extraordinary Ordinaryes, which no Catholique can grant; and therfore, as I ſayd, <hi>M. Doctour</hi> muſt anſwere his owne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16320:10"/>arguments, drawne from the diuine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (for according to that ground, we muſt in England haue properly an Ordinary) &amp; come to confeſſe, that there is no diuine <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue Precept,</hi> for his Holineſſe to appoynt vs in England a Biſhop, but only a diuine <hi>naturall command</hi> to prouide vs of all things, neceſſary to ſaluation, whether by Biſhops, or other meanes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="question">
            <head>THE II. QVESTION. <hi>Whether without a Bishop there can be a particular Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE ſubſtance of all that is conteyned in the firſt 16. numbers of the <hi>Reply,</hi> is taken out of the <hi>Inquiſition ſect.</hi> 3. and <hi>ſect.</hi> 6 about the wordes of <hi>S. Cyprian: The Church is a people vnited to the Bishop,</hi> and, <hi>the neceſſity of a particular Bishop to make a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church;</hi> which points are cleared by the <hi>Qualificatour</hi> in the ſame <hi>Sections.</hi> And the Reader of himſelfe may anſwere all his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, if he remember how the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> expreſſy teacheth; That in ſome particular Churches, there muſt be particular Biſhops, diſtinct from the Pope: That in England while we wanted Biſhops, properly called <hi>Ordinaryes</hi> in an ordinary manner, the Pope could be, was, and is our ſole particular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: That theſe words of <hi>S. Cyprian (The Church is a people vnited to the Bishop)</hi> as they were ſpoken by him, preciſely, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; formally, ſignify, that a people deuided from their lawfull Biſhop is no church, but a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16320:11"/>Schiſmaticall multitude, &amp; not only by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as the <hi>Replyer u.</hi> 9.13. &amp; in other places doth ſuppoſe; &amp; out of that his owne ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, deduceth abſurdities agaynſt the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſour,</hi> as not diſtinguiſhing betwixt meere inculpable want of a Biſhop, and ſinfull ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from a Biſhop: Whereas indeede <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> only ſpeaketh of ſinnefull ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; therfore affirmeth, that ſuch as are not vnited with a Biſhop, in the ſenſe he ſpake, are not in the Church: That Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like writers, may fitly agaynſt heretickes, inferre out of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> a neceſſity of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Biſhops in Gods Church; becauſe it were no crime of Schiſme to be deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Biſhop, if in the Church there ought not to be Biſhops: That the ſayd wordes of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> may be taken for a definition of the Church, if the word <hi>Bishop</hi> be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indefini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely of a particular Biſhop diſtinct from the Pope, or for the Pope himſelfe. For no multitude, can be a Church, without vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther to a particular Biſhop vnder the Pope or to the Pope himſelfe. <hi>Without Vnion</hi> (I ſay) eyther <hi>actuall,</hi> or <hi>aptitudinall, really,</hi> or <hi>in readineſse</hi> of will, to accept one, when he ſhall be lawfully giuen them; which promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude they may, and ought to haue, when actually they want one. The <hi>Replyer</hi> himſelf muſt yield that <hi>S. Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> if he meane of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Vnion with a Biſhop (as he would haue him to meane) can not be vnderſtood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatly of a particular Biſhop diſtinct fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope, vnleſſe he will teach it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the very definition, and eſſence of a
<pb facs="tcp:16320:11"/>particular Church to haue the Pope for its particular Biſhop, which I am ſure he will not auerre. For who dare ſay, that the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular dioceſſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath the Pope for its ſole Biſhop, is no particular Church?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thus is anſwered all that he alead geth out of <hi>Bellarmine, Stapleton,</hi> &amp;c. who only teach, that in the Church there muſt be ſome particular Biſhops, and that the Church, is a people, vnted to the Biſhop, in the manner I haue now declared. Yea all that I haue ſaid is much confirmed, by what the <hi>Replier</hi> citeth out of <hi>Stapleton;</hi> That the word (Church) in ſcripture, ſignifyeth properly, not a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, headleſſe multitude, but a multitude to which Paſtours and Prelates are conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by God. For I trow, Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, were no vagrant, headleſſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as longe as they were, and are gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt his Vicar. And the <hi>Replyers</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection <hi>n.</hi> 9. That euery Catholicke family, euery Nunnery, yea and Company of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke women, ſhoulde be a particular Church, if vnion to the Pope were ſufficient, to conſtitute a particular Church; is eaſily anſwered, by demaunding of him, whether in a Dioceſſe, enioying its particular Biſhop, euery Nunnery, euery family, euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Catholicke, be a particular Church? what he ſhall anſwere in that ſuppoſition, the ſame I anſwere in our caſe, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Pope for our particular Biſhop. <hi>S. Paul</hi> faluteth the Church in the houſe of <hi>Nimpha, Coloſs. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>v. 15.</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Philemon, ad Philem. v. 2.</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16320:12"/>
               <hi>S. Gregory Thanmaturgus,</hi> at firſt, had for his particular <hi>Church</hi> only 17. Catholiks, nor are we certayne that they were not in one houſe or family. But to my purpoſe it importeth nothing, and therfore I will not diſpute, whether one family can be fitly called a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Heere commeth, of it ſelfe, a ready an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, to another obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Replyer.</hi> To ſhew that the ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cited wordes of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> cannot inferre, that a Biſhop is neceſſary, to make a particular <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Diſcuſsourn.</hi> 6. retorteth them in this manner: Whoſoeuer are not in ſchiſme with any lawfull Biſhop, doe fulfill the definition of <hi>S. Cyprian:</hi> But thoſe who without their owne fault haue no Biſhop, are not in ſchiſme with any lawfull Biſhopp; <hi>Ergo,</hi> thoſe who haue no Biſhop, do fulfill the definition of <hi>S. Cyprian.</hi> This argument, the <hi>Replyer</hi> would returne vpon the <hi>Diſcuſsour,</hi> by ſaying; That ſeeing a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke family, without a Biſhop, is not in ſchiſme with any Biſhop, it would follow, that ſuch a family, conſidered by it ſelfe, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth the definition of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is a Church. But the anſwere is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready giuen. If one man, or family, may be tearmed a particular Church, in caſe they were poſitiuely vnited to a particular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, much more may they be a Church in <hi>S. Cyprians</hi> ſenſe, which requireth not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue vnion, but only, that they be not deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from their Biſhop. If one man, or family, be not capable of the denomination of a particular Church, then his obiection tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16320:12"/>not the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> whoſe argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in reſpect of a multitude, <hi>Plebs,</hi> and <hi>Grex,</hi> a people, and multitude (ſuch as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Catholickes are) capable of the ſayd denomination, if other requiſite conditions were not wantinge. Still then it is trew, as the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> inferred, That a people, not deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their lawful Biſhop, is according to <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> a true Church, although they haue no actual vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with a particular Biſhop.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His proofes <hi>n.</hi> 17. That <hi>M. Doctour</hi> was not iniurious to Engliſh Catholicks by ſaying; They did not fulfill the definition of a Church, giuen by <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> while they wanted a Biſhop, do ſtill relye vpon a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not ſolide: to wit, that <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> by a people vnited to their Biſhop, vnderſtands a poſitiue Vnion with a Biſhop; wheras <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Smith</hi> proued out S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> words, and whole drift, that by Vnion with a Biſhop, he vnderſtands only, that the people be not deuided from him, &amp; this ſuppoſed, it cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followeth: That if Engliſh Catholikes, did not fulfill the ſayd definition, they muſt be taxed of diuiſion from a Biſhop, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of Schiſme.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Diſcuſſour q. 2. n. 8. 13.</hi> and the <hi>Qualificatour ſect. 7.</hi> anſwere all he bringeth to proue, that the Pope was not our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Biſhop: and the <hi>Qualificatour</hi> ſheweth, that <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> doth not argue, <hi>à poſſibili ad eſſe.</hi> But (ſayth the <hi>Replyer n. 21.</hi>) if when a Church is depriued of Biſhops, the Pope remayne their particular Biſhop, no Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke ſhould euer be vacant, nor any Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16320:13"/>want a Rectour, or Prouince a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall, becauſe the Prouinciall would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Rectour, &amp; the Generall Prouinciall. And if <hi>per impoſſibile,</hi> there were neuer a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in all the Church, but the Pope; the Church ſhould ſtill be Hierarchical, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of diuers particular Churches.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I anſwere: This argument muſt be ſolued, by the <hi>Replyer</hi> himſelfe; who in the next number granteth, that the Pope may be the particular Biſhop, of a particular Church; and yet he would not admit, that he may make himſelf ſole particular Biſhop of all Churches. The reaſon is; becauſe our Sauiour hath inſtituted, that there ſhould be ſome particular Churches, gouerned by Biſhops diſtinct from the ſupreme Paſtour; not becauſe the Pope alone cannot make a particular Church, but becauſe, he can not make all Churches particular Churches, in the manner our Sauiour hath inſtituted, by their proper Eccleſiaſticall Princes, diſtinct from the Pope, as is required in a Hierarchy. In this ſenſe, Biſhoprickes are ſayd to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>acant,</hi> becauſe they want a Biſhop, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Pope.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And heere I muſt obſerue, that it is ſo true, that a Church without a Biſhop, may be a particular Church, that the <hi>Replyer</hi> while he is ſpeaking againſt it, ſpeakes for it, by ſaying, That a Biſhopricke may be Vacant. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſay I, by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>acancy,</hi> it ceaſeth not to be a Biſhopricke, a Dioceſſe, a Church. If a Church, ſurely not an Vniuerſall, but a particular one. When the Biſhop of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16320:13"/>Church dyeth, do they not demaund a Biſhop for ſuch a Church? <hi>Ergo,</hi> they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that it ſtil remayneth a Church. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe when a Biſhop was demaunded for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, it might haue bynne anſwered: Firſt fynde a Church in Englande, and then aske a Biſhop for the Church of Englande. <hi>M. Doctour pag. 378. n.</hi> 3. ſayth: that when a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop cannot be had, the particular Church, muſt be gouerned, as it may. And <hi>pag.</hi> 374. alluding to Englande, he ſayth. If for a tyme ſome particular Church be gouerned by Prieſts, or an Archprieſt without a Biſhop, it is a thing accidentall &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> a Church, &amp; Englande in particular, without a Biſhop, may be, and was a particular Church. And indeed we can not teach otherwiſe, vnleſſe by the death of euery Biſhop, we will haue all men become ſpeachleſſe. For, when the Biſhop of a particular Church dyeth, how can we expreſſe it, but by ſayinge, ſuch a Church hath loſt its Biſhop? The ſame is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, euen out of the other examples, alledged by the <hi>Replyer.</hi> For by the death of a Rectour, or Prouinciall, the Colledge cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to be a Colledge, nor the Prouince, a Prouince: neyther doth it follow, that a Prouinciall, or Generall vpon the death of euery Rectour, or Prouinciall, muſt becom Rectours &amp; Prouinciaſs. The reaſon of this dependeth on the knowledge of particular inſtitutes of Religion. In generall it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſay, that no Generall, hath ouer his whole Order, ſo abſolute, and vnlimited extent of power, as the Pope, by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16320:14"/>inſtitution, hath ouer the whole, &amp; euery member of Gods Church. I grant, in Catholike Countreys, where after the death of the Biſhop, other officers remaine, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne till a new Biſhop be elected, the Pope need not actuate his immediate power &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorſhip, as he is obliged to do in countries wholy &amp; for a long time deſtitute of Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Becauſe the Pope hath immediate power ouer all particular Churches, and is <hi>Proprius Pastor</hi> of England, and all other countreys; to make himſelfe particular ſole Biſhop of any church, he needs not take the name, of that particular church, but begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be ſole Biſhop, as ſoone as it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be deſtitute of a Biſhop. But other particular Biſhops who haue no ſuch vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, immediate power, muſt acquire it, by a new Title to their particular Churches. And ſeeing the Pope in reſpect of England, hath indeed performed the Office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, no doubt but he would alſo call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Biſhop of England, if, with the <hi>Replyer,</hi> he conceaued, that there were a diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to make England a particular Church, and that to make it ſuch, it were neceſſary, and ſufficient, that he tooke the name or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it, as the <hi>Replyer n. 22.</hi> confeſſeth. For who will ſay, that for a matter of no more difficulty, then is to take a <hi>Name,</hi> the Pope will breake a diuine commaund? It is then a ſigne, that he may make vs a particular Church, without calling himſelfe Biſhop of England, becauſe in very deed ſo he is. His Holyneſſe ſtyleth not himſelfe Biſhop of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16320:14"/>Holland, where neuertheleſſe he hath a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, which ſuppoſeth the Pope to be the particular Biſhop of that countrey. For a Church cannot be a particular Church, by vnion to a Vicar, but by vnion to him, whoſe Vicar he is. My Lord of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> is not called Biſhop of England, or of any Church, or Dioceſſe thereof; and yet the <hi>Replyer</hi> thinkes, he maketh vs a particular Church, becauſe he hath the power of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of England, which no man can deny the Pope to haue, in as immediate and more ample high manner: and therefore he may make vs a particular Church, although he take not the Name therof.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Yea, wheras the <hi>Replyer n. 22.23.</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Pope could not be particular Biſhop of England, vnleſſe he did eyther the office of a Biſhop himſelfe, or by his Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, or as leſt ſtyled himſelfe Biſhop of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: I anſwere; that it is ſufficient he do the Office of a Biſhop, according as the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the tyme, and place permit, or require; which his Holineſſe moſt carful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath and doth performe, by ſending into England Prieſts, or alſo a Biſhop with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from him delegated &amp;c. and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> pleades agaynſt himſelfe, telling vs in effect, that the Pope, by the very delegating my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and not making him Biſhop of England hath declared himſelf to be, the ſole particular Biſhop of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where he doth the office of a Biſhop by his Delegates. As <hi>Ireland</hi> is not a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in reſpect of his Maieſties Deputy but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16320:15"/>becauſe it is vnited to his Maieſty, as to its King: ſo <hi>England</hi> cannot be a particular Church, in reſpect of my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> but in regard of the Pope, whoſe Deputy my Lord is, being not ſpirituall Prince, and Biſhop of <hi>England.</hi> If to be Ordinary in an extraordinary manner, be ſufficient to make vs a Church, how will the <hi>Replyer</hi> proue, that before my lord of <hi>Chalcedons</hi> comming, his Holineſſes Nuntio in <hi>Paris,</hi> did not make vs a particular Church?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Againſt the <hi>Diſcuſsours</hi> doctrine <hi>n.</hi> 11. That perſons exempt from all Biſhops, and ſubiect only to the Pope, are a particular Church, without a particular Biſhop; the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 26. obiecteth, That Monaſteryes, ſubiect only to the Pope, are no particular Churches, vnles we wil make euery Nunnery of women, a particular Church. I anſwere, the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> ſpeaketh in generall, of places, and perſons, exempt from Biſhops. And it is well knowne, that there be diuers Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, of extent, ſufficient to make a Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ſubiect to no Biſhop. Theſe <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> affirmes to be particular churches. One Monaſtery, or Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nery, immediatly ſubiect to the Pope, are as much a particular Church, as if they had a particular Biſhop, as we ſayd aboue <hi>n.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In his <hi>numbers</hi> 28.29. he teacheth, that it is a great Luſtre to a Church to haue a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Biſhop: That a Church gouerned by a Delegate, wanteth ſome perfection of that, which is gouerned by an Ordinary: That if a Pope ſhould ſend a Prieſt into <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16320:15"/>with power to confirme, <hi>England</hi> ſhould be in its kind a particular Church, but not in the degree and perfection, as if it had an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Biſhop. What? Is the neceſſity of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a Biſhop come only to a <hi>greater Lustre?</hi> Muſt Catholickes be troden vnder foote for a greater luſtre? Doth all this diſpute end in degrees of Compariſon? Hath our being, or not being a particular Church, ſo great latitude, that it may reach to a Church with a Biſhop Ordinary, a Biſhop Delegate, a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Prieſt? I confeſſe the <hi>Replyer</hi> is forced to ſteppe backe, and not to ſtand ſo punctually on his ground, of Englands not being a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, without a Biſhop. I deſire he would ſpeake plainly. Doth the diuine law, in theſe ſore tymes, oblige vs to be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, in the greateſt perfection you mention, by a Biſhop Ordinary? You wil not ſay ſo. Is the diuine law, of our being a particular Church well ſatisfied, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons endued with authority, ſufficient, and proportionable to theſe dayes, let them be Prieſts, or Biſhops, Ordinaryes, or Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? So you muſt ſay. Let vs then ſpeake no more of being a particular Church, or of hauing determinatly a Biſhop, by the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine law; but let our care be, in the ſight of God, vnpartially to conſider, and with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency to deſire, what may be moſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for Catholickes, not in <hi>France, Spayne, Italy,</hi> and other Countreyes, happy with peaceable poſſeſſion of Eccleſiaſticall ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour; but in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> bleſſed only with ioyful ſuffering a longe continued perſecution.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16320:16"/>12. Well, to leaue ſpeculations, &amp; School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynts, ſeing you conſtantly perſiſt in this, that without a Biſhop we cannot be a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church; before you burthen our conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences, with a heauy obligation, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe our being a particular Church, with hazard of goods, liberty, and life; you muſt not blame vs, if we requeſt you, to produce ſome precept of God, or the Church, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding vs to be a particular Church, in your ſenſe: &amp; why we may not content our ſelues, with being good Catholickes, and members of the Vniuerſall Church, as <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Smith n.</hi> 14. propoſed to <hi>M. Doctour?</hi> In this conſiſteth the poynt of the difficulty. The <hi>Replyer</hi> anſwereth, that this demaund is by the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> brought out of its place, &amp; ſo muſt expect anſwere in the next queſtion, which treateth, Whether by the diuine law, euery particular Church, muſt haue its Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop? What is this, but to auoyd the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty? for <hi>M. Doctour</hi> propoſeth as two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or titles, <hi>The deuine precept</hi> of hauing a Biſhop in euery particular Church, and, <hi>The neceſſity</hi> of hauing a Biſhop, becauſe without him we cannot be a <hi>particular Church,</hi> as may be ſeene <hi>Chap. 14. n. 4. 5. 6. 7.</hi> and in other places. Now the <hi>Replyer</hi> will make <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> walke in a circle, and proue, that we are bound to be a particular Church, becauſe we are obliged to haue a Biſhop; and we are obliged to haue a Biſhop, becauſe we are bound to be a particular Church. If the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> will defend <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> he muſt tell vs, what commaund we haue, preciſely to be a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16320:16"/>particular Church, ſo that, if a Biſhop were not neceſſary in other reſpects, yet for this cauſe alone, he could not be refuſed. This the <hi>Replyer</hi> doth not proue in the next que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, nor is it a thing, in it ſelfe, factible or credible.</p>
            <p n="13">13. From the <hi>number</hi> 13. to the end of this Queſtion, he taxeth the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> as ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>M. Doctours</hi> wordes <hi>Chap. 14. n. 9.</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then he intended. But thoſe wordes which he ſeeketh to defend, muſt eyther teach as farre, as the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> extendeth them, or elſe they will come short of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>M. Doctours</hi> purpoſe. For if it be as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to haue a particular Biſhop, to make a particular church, as to haue an Vniuerſall Biſhop, for the making an Vniuerſal church; and that, by the diuine law euery country of extent muſt be a particular Church; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth clearly, that according to <hi>M. Doctour</hi> there is as much neceſſity to haue a Biſhop in <hi>England.</hi> which in his opinion is a particular church of extent, as to haue a Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> You will perhaps ſay, that the diuine Law, of hauing a particular Biſhop, in euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular church, doth not ſo generally bynd, as the other doth, but may ceaſe to oblige, by reaſon of ſome particular circumſtances of tyme, or place. This anſwere ouerthoweth <hi>M. Doctours</hi> whole edifice. Becauſe if any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may take away the obligation of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine law, certainly a generall perſecution, threatned to a whole Countrey, may free vs from ſuch a bond. How then will <hi>M. Doctour</hi> conclude, that by the diuyne law we are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16320:17"/>bound to haue a Biſhop, in a caſe, wherein the diuine law ceaſeth to bynd? You ſee the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> had reaſon to ſay, That <hi>M. Doctours</hi> wordes imported too much, or elſe you muſt yeald, they proued too litle.</p>
            <p n="14">14. In like manner what <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſayd, in the ſame place; That vnleſſe euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular church haue a Biſhop, the Vniuerſall church ſhould not, as Chriſt hath inſtituted, be a Hierarchy, compoſed of diuers particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar churches, is rightly taxed by the <hi>Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour,</hi> as eyther not ſound, or not ſufficient for <hi>M. Doctours</hi> purpoſe. If it be vnderſtood only indeterminatly, that is, The whole church cannot be a Hierarchy, vnleſſe ſome particular churches haue Biſhops it proueth not, that <hi>England</hi> muſt haue a Biſhop: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, although <hi>England</hi> want a Biſhop, other churches may haue them, &amp; ſo the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall church remayne a Hierarchy. If he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand of euery determinate particular church; then it followeth, that the church of God cannot be a Hierarchy vnles the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate particular church of <hi>England</hi> haue a Biſhop, as the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> vrged <hi>n.</hi> 16. and the <hi>Replyer</hi> doth not confute.</p>
            <p n="15">15. By the way I eſpy in his <hi>n.</hi> 32. a word for my purpoſe, which ouerthroweth the <hi>Repliers</hi> whole diſcourſe in this Queſtion. The church (ſayth he) cannot be at al with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſupreme Biſhop, or not without <hi>order to him,</hi> when the ſea is Vacant. This I take as granted, and very true: and hence I inferre; That as the Vniuerſall church may be an Vniuerſall church, without actuall vnion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16320:17"/>to a ſupreme Biſhop, while the ſea is Vacant, becauſe it ſtill hath <hi>Order,</hi> reference, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to be gouerned by an Vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, as ſoone as he ſhall be elected; ſo a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular church, may be ſuch, by <hi>Order,</hi> and aptitude to be vnited with a particular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, whenſoeuer he ſhall be appoynted; &amp; ſo <hi>S. Cyprians</hi> definition <hi>(The Church is the people vnited to the Bishop)</hi> doth not require, that the people be actually vnited to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, but only in readines of mynd, or apti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinally. And thus <hi>England</hi> while it wanted a Biſhop, was a particular church, becauſe it was alwayes in diſpoſition to be vnited to a Biſhop. Where now is that argument, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten inculcated by <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> the <hi>Inquiſitour,</hi> and the <hi>Replyer? S. Cyprian</hi> defines a church to be the people vnited to the Biſhop. But the people cannot be vnited to a Biſhop, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they haue one: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they cannot be a church vnleſſe they haue a Biſhop. For the <hi>Replyer</hi> himſelfe hath told vs, that when the Sea is vacant, the people may be a church, with only <hi>Order</hi> to a Biſhop, which implyeth not the actuall hauing a Biſhop, but only a fit diſpoſition to haue one.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="question">
            <head>THE III. QVESTION. <hi>Whether by the diuine Law euery particular Church must haue its Bishop?</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE diuine precept, of hauing Biſhops in the Church, is only to be vnderſtod indeterminatly, or in generall; that in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16320:18"/>the whole church, there muſt be ſome Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as many, or few, as may be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or requiſite, to the end of gouerning the ſame Church. But in reſpect of particular, and determinate churches, the commaund is not abſolute, but beareth a great reſpect to circumſtances of tyme, place, and the like, as the Vicar of Chriſt ſhall iudge it beſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for gouerning, and prouiding ſuch churches of al things neceſſary to ſaluation. Wherfore from the diuine precept, of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Biſhops, in generall, we cannot infer a neceſſity of hauing Biſhops, in this, or that particular countrey although otherwiſe of extent. For there may occur good reaſon, why ſome other gouernment, in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular circumſtances may conduce more to the glory of God, and particular good of ſuch a country. Contrarywiſe it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that ſome church of ſmall extent, may in particular circumſtances more require the gouernment of a Biſhop, then a larger coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. The thing therfore which is (as I may ſay) formally to be conſidered, is the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or greater, or leſſe neceſſity; not the greater, or leſſe quantity of place, or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons, but in as much as theſe may induce, a greater neceſſity of hauing Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For this cauſe, in the primitiue church, euen in tyme of hoateſt perſecution, Biſhops were multiplied, and placed in diuers Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, becauſe thoſe tymes did ſo require. In ſo much, that ſome Authors write, that in thoſe firſt dayes of Chriſtianity, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16320:18"/>all Prieſts were Biſhops, contrary to the preſent practiſe of Gods church. The reaſon was, the paucity of Prieſts, of which if many had not binne made Biſhops, to ordayne Prieſts, particular churches would haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned vnfurniſhed of Prieſts, to conuert infidells, &amp; aſſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being conuerted. Euery church hauing inough to do within it ſelf, could not affoard help to others. For this ſame cauſe, Biſhops were allotted to ſmaller flockes, then is now eyther vſuall, or lawful, to be commonly practiſed. <hi>S. Gregory</hi> the <hi>Thaumaturge,</hi> cited by the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 14. was created Biſhop ouer only 17. perſons. A num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber competent for thoſe old, not theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tymes, in places where by neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churches, the want of other may be relieued. The more the Vniuerſall church is dilated, the leſſe euery particular church needeth a a Biſhop of its own. Becauſe other churches, without much preiudice vnto themſelues, may frequently, lend them a helping hand. In countreys, by vaſt diſtance, remote from helpe, and comfort of Chriſtian Nations, a Biſhop may be needfull for a few. In <hi>Europe,</hi> the caſe is otherwiſe. If one ſhippe be in want, it can becken to thoſe who abound in diuers others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence it followeth, that, to proue the neceſſity of a Biſhop in <hi>England</hi> in vayne we haue recourſe, to the diuine precept in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of hauing ſome Biſhops in the church. All the queſtion muſt ſetle on this; Whether <hi>England,</hi> can be ſufficiently furniſhed of Prieſts, and prouided of all neceſſaries for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16320:19"/>our iourney to heauen, without a Biſhop; Or whether the inconueniece of comming, might not counterpoyſe the commodityes he would bring. This ſhould be the only Queſtion; and the anſwere ought to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to the ſame Biſhop, to whoſe charge Chriſt hath committed <hi>England,</hi> &amp; all other countreys. In the meane tyme, let not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes be frighted, with diuine precepts where none are.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Replyer</hi> doth not rightly ſtate the Queſtion, while he telleth vs <hi>n.</hi> 8. that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> only teacheth, that Catholickes cannot refuſe a Biſhop, although by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming perſecution ſhould be increaſed, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing he be ſent by lawfull authority. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſayth he) in that caſe, the Pope ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declareth, that the diuine law ceaſeth not to oblige. A goodly conſtruction of <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> meaning, and a fayre account of all his paynes; which are reduced to this iſſue: Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes are bound, by the diuine law, to receaue a Biſhop, if the Pope declare, that the diuine law, of hauing a Biſhop, byndeth them. As if the Queſtion were, whether Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes be obliged, to belieue the Popes declarations, whether or no diuine Lawes do oblige. Surely for this, there need no wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Hierarchyes, Inquiſitions, <hi>Replyes.</hi> The anſwere might ſpeedly haue binne gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. That in all things, the Catholickes of <hi>England</hi> haue binne, are, and eternally will be, as zealous, prompt, and conſtant in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting their vnderſtandings, and wills, to the commaunders, or declarations of his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16320:19"/>Holines, as any Catholickes whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Sunne beholdeth. But it is euident, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſpeaketh abſolutly, and <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> of the neceſſity we haue, to receaue a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, abſtracting from the Popes declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Miſſion. This, his reaſons demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, drawne from the diuine precept of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge Biſhops in euery great parte of the church; from the vtility, or neceſſity of Confirmation, without which men are in danger to forſake their faith, as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> vrgeth <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as may be ſeene in the very title, and throughout his whole 14. Chapter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Neyther is it a good Conſequence: The Pope ſendeth a Bishop to England, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he declares, that there is a diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, to haue a Bishop in <hi>England.</hi> Many thinges are holily done, which a man is not obliged to do. When the Pope maketh a Dioceſſe, and endueth it with a Bishop, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from other particular Bishops, doth he therfore declare, that there was a diuine precept, to make ſuch a Dioceſſe, or to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce a Bishop in it? We ſee ſome Territoryes, capable of Bishops, to be gouerned by Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots which could not be, if there were a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine precept, to place Bishops in ſuch Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritoryes, although it had not likewiſe binne againſt the diuine law, to haue placed Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops in the ſame Territoryes. This is a good Inference. The Pope, for many yeares, ſent vs no Bishop: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he iudged there was no diuine precept, obliginge him to ſend vs one; but the other conſequence is of no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, as I haue shewed. Will the <hi>Replyer</hi> admit
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16320:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16320:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16320:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16320:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16320:22"/>this argument; The Pope for many yeares left vs without a Biſhop: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he iudged there was a diuine precept, that we ſhould be left without a Biſhop?. It is as good as his. <hi>Nicolas Smith n.</hi> 4. ſayd truly; The delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about ſending a Biſhop to <hi>England,</hi> was only, <hi>Quid expediret,</hi> what was expedient, not what was neceſſary, by the diuine law, which, as I ſayd, is only of Churches taken in generall and indeterminately. And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but eſteeme it iniurious, to thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly bowelles of his Holines, to thinke, that he euer iudged vs obliged, to accept a Biſhop, with a generall increaſe of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If he were perſuaded, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a Biſhop, would occaſion to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, a generall perſecution, I dare ſay, he would neuer impoſe vpon them ſuch an obligation. And yet <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> and the <hi>Replyer</hi> are rigid Cenſurers of Catholickes, as infingers of the diuine Law, if they ſhould refuſe a Biſhop, euen vpon that heauy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Suppoſing the Inſtitution of hauing Biſhops, do not oblige in all tymes, places, and other circumſtances, <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> had had reaſon to ſay, <hi>n.</hi> 4. That <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> if he will ſpeake home, muſt proue, not only that there is a diuine precept for vs to haue a Biſhop, but alſo that no perſecution can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the obligation thereof, or yield ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe of diſpenſation. For although we ſhould grant, a diuine precept in generall, yet if in ſome circumſtances it do not bynd, the tranſgreſſours ſhould not ſinne. Now, if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16320:22"/>any cauſe may affoard a lawfull excuſe, what can be greater, then the auoyding of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perſecution, wherby not only goods, and life, but alſo chriſtian ſoules are expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to danger.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 3. ſpeaketh in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as one would conceaue <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> to haue affirmed, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> denyed the Pope may diſpence in the diuine Law; which <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer ſayd: yet becauſe the <hi>Replyer</hi> firſt mentioneth this matter, I muſt adde, that ſeeing <hi>M. Doctour</hi> proueth our obligation to haue a Biſhop, by the neceſſity of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and danger of denying our faith, through want of that Sacramet; it wil not be eaſy for him, to defend, that the Pope can diſpence in that obligation. For what diſpenſation can be giuen, for expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of mens ſoules to damnation? Or if <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> and the <hi>Replyer</hi> grant, that the Pope may diſpenſe in this commaund; I muſt be bold to ſay, their arguments, drawne from the neceſsity of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> are farre-fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched frights, not ſolid reaſons.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Wheras the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 12. writeth, that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> ſayd not truly, that in <hi>England</hi> the multitude of Catholickes, not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the place, is only to be conſidered: I ſay truly, that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> ſayth no ſuch matter, but only, <hi>That if England be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, not materially, but formally (as Deuines expreſſe themſelues) that is, not the extent of land, or multitude of people, but the number of Catholickes, which only can make a trae Church, we shall find it to be more then ſarre from a great,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16320:23"/>or notabic part of the Catholicke Church ſpread ouer the whole word.</hi> Whether or no the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of place, or number of perſons, although not Catholickes, be alſo conſiderable, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Smith</hi> would anſwere, that it depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon other circumſtances, which may make ſuch an extent, more, or leſſe, or not at all, conſiderable, as we haue ſhewed <hi>n.</hi> 2. As for <hi>England</hi> in particular, if the extent of place were leſſe, a Biſhop would be more vſefull, for the Sacrament of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which might be adminiſtred to more, if they were leſſe diſtant in place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And this vrgeth much agaynſt the <hi>Replyer,</hi> who, in prouing the neceſſity of a Biſhop in euery great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, finally <hi>n.</hi> 20. reduceth all, to the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. It is ſtrange, how zealous the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 10. is againſt <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> for makinge the Catholicks, <hi>as it were a contemptible num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> only becauſe he ſayth, they are not a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table great part of Gods Church, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> cited in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, a Writing entituled; <hi>A Paratell &amp;c.</hi> (the Author whereof, is thought to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of greater ranke, then the <hi>Replyer</hi>) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin it is ſayd, that all our Catholickes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, would ſcarcſely make one, of diuers Biſhoprickes in <hi>England.</hi> And it is worth the noting, that the Paralelliſt ſayd ſo, in proofe, that ſome Regulars, who wrote that the gouernment of certayne Churches, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently belonged to them, did therby make a greater Challenge, then my lord of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> which ſurely muſt haue reſpect only
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16320:23"/>to the number of perſons, and not extent of place. For thoſe Regulars neuer chalenged power ouer all Catholickes, through <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> as my lord of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> doth. But by this we may ſee, how the number of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes muſt be rayſed, or cryed downe, as it maketh moſt for their purpoſe. It ſeemeth his Holines had conſideration, cheifly of <hi>Perſons,</hi> not of the <hi>Place,</hi> by makinge my Lord, not Biſhop of the countrey, but only giuing him authority referred to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Ordinaries haue iuriſdiction, in reſpect both of place, and perſon, Catholickes, and Heretiques: and therfore in them, extent of place is much more conſiderable. Laſtly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were granted (as a thing not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king much for our preſent purpoſe) that the extent of place in <hi>England,</hi> were much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, thence at the moſt could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that <hi>England</hi> is capable of a Biſhop, not that it muſt of neceſſity haue one, which is our only Queſtion. As there be ſome Dioceſſes, for extent of place, wel capable of too, or more Biſhops, and yet it doth not follow, that of neceſsity they muſt haue too or more, if by one they can be ſufficiently gouerned; yea there are diuers places, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of one, or more Biſhops, who haue no Biſhop at all, but are gouerned by other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Likewiſe the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 9. about this poynt, citeth the wordes of the <hi>Diſcuſſour n.</hi> 7. very imperfectly in this manner. To af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that one Dioceſſe, or Citty, is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table part of the Church, is a thinge, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16320:24"/>no deuine, yea no man of iudgment will ſay. The words entirely cited are theſe: <hi>To affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that one Dioceſſe, or City, or indeed not ſo much as one Dioceſſe or Citty, is a great, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table part of that Chuch, which reacheth, as farre as the riſing and ſetting of the Sunne, and that it must therfore,</hi> iure diuino, <hi>by the diuine law, haue a Bishop; ſo as no cauſe can excuſe the want of one, is a thing, which no Deuine &amp;c.</hi> This ſaying of <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> is ſo euident, as no man can deny it to be true; and yet for this ſpeach, he is deeply charged by the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> and <hi>Replyer</hi> of great immodeſty. Beſides <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> neuer ſay d <hi>M. Doctour</hi> affirmed all this, but only by good conſequence, he ſhewed that this and diuers other hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, muſt follow out of his Principles.</p>
            <p n="11">11. What he citeth <hi>n.</hi> 14. out of the Regulars Anſwere, to my Lord of <hi>Calcedons</hi> letter, is by him odiouſly forced, to a ſenſe by the neyther meant, nor written. It is cleare, they ſpeake not of Epiſcopall authority in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but of a Biſhop, in theſe tymes, with power of Ordinary, <hi>in foro externo,</hi> coactiue, to erect a Tribunall &amp;c. which they ſay, would in theſe tymes, proue pernicions to ſoules &amp;c. as <hi>M. Doctour Chap.</hi> 15. confeſſeth, my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> to ſay, that ſuch a Tribunal is not ſutable to theſe tymes. Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is a holy thinge, and as auncient, as our Sauiour Chriſt; yet to do it publickly, in theſe tymes, may be called, a Nouelty, and pernicious to Catholikes.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In more then three whole leaues, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>n.</hi> 16. he laboureth to make good, that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16320:24"/>fauoureth <hi>M. Doctour.</hi> All his diſcourſe is reduced to this. When <hi>Sotus</hi> teacheth it, to be of diuine law, that <hi>in generall to euery Church according to the Eccleſiaſticall diuiſion, proper Bishops are to be applyed;</hi> thoſe wordes <hi>(in generall)</hi> are to be interpreted, as if one ſhould ſay, Chriſt in generall hath ordayned, that euery man ſhall be baptized, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by our Sauiours commaund, euery particular man is to be baptized. The <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſour</hi> interpreteth <hi>Sotus</hi> by the word <hi>(inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall)</hi> to meane <hi>indeterminatly</hi> of ſome Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes according as particular circumſtances of perſons, tyme, and place ſhall require, &amp; not that <hi>Sotus</hi> did teach an abſolute precept, of placing Biſhops in euery determinate par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Dioceſſe. This interpretation, is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of <hi>Sotus</hi> his whole drift, which was to proue afterward agaynſt <hi>Catharines,</hi> that the Reſidence of Biſhops, is <hi>de iure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino,</hi> of the diuine law; and alſo out of his wordes, cited by the <hi>Replyer n. 22.</hi> that the Biſhop muſt, <hi>adſalutem gregis oculate attende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> looke as it were with his eye, to the good of his flocke: &amp;, <hi>propter peculiarem curam &amp; vigilantiam;</hi> for the peculiar care and vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy neceſſary to his Church. All which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate <hi>Sotus</hi> his meaning only to be, that Biſhops, by the diuine law muſt be ſo apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to particular Churches, as may ſuffice for the good gouernment of the ſame, but not ſo abſolutely, that when they may be otherwiſe prouided for, euery Dioceſe muſt of neceſſity haue its Biſhop; which <hi>Sotus</hi> knew well to be agaynſt the practiſe of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16320:25"/>Church, wherin diuers Territoryes, as great as Dioceſſes, are exempt from all particular Biſhops. As <hi>Sotus</hi> teacheth, that Biſhops muſt be applyed to particular Dioceſſes; ſo he teacheth, that Pariſh Prieſts muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to particular Pariſhes, as may be ſeene in the wordes cited by the <hi>Replyer;</hi> &amp; it were ſtrange, that <hi>Sotus</hi> ſhould therfore be allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to hold, it a diuine law, that euery Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, haue its Pariſh Prieſt, if otherwiſe it be ſufficiently prouided. <hi>Sotus</hi> then muſt be vnderſtoode, only indeterminately, that ſome Dioceſſes muſt haue their Biſhops, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe they cannot be ſufficiently gouerned; but not abſolutely, that by the diuine law ech one muſt haue its Biſhop, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though otherwiſe it can be furniſhed with all neceſſaryes. And this in effect is no more then we ſayd in this Queſtion <hi>n.</hi> 1. and euin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, the no neceſsity of a Biſhop in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, by the diuine law, if without a Biſhop we can be ſufficiently prouided for. According to this true meaning of <hi>Sotus,</hi> it followeth not, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> thinkes; <hi>Sotus</hi> teacheth, that there muſt be a Biſhop in euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Dioceſſe: <hi>Ergo</hi> much more in euery nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the Church; becauſe if a notable part of the Church, can be otherwiſe well gouerned, it will no more, according to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> require a Biſhop, then a particular Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Yea there may happe to be a greater o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation, of placing a Biſhop, in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Dioceſſe, then in a great Country, where the Biſhop cannot performe his office or cannot come without great domage to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16320:25"/>Catholikes, which are conſiderations depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wholly vpon particular circumſtances, and not to be determined by <hi>generall notions</hi> of greater, or leſſe extent of place. Beſides, <hi>M. Doctour</hi> alleadged <hi>Sotus</hi> abſolutely; now the <hi>Replyer</hi> hath recourſe to inferences. If <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> meane as the <hi>Replyer</hi> will haue him; That by the diuine lawe, the Pope muſt apply a particular Biſhop to euery Dioceſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to euery place capable to be a Dioceſſe, the doctrine is not true in it ſelfe; and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the <hi>Replier pag. 30. n. 12.</hi> who granteth that the Pope may gouerne ſome litle Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, otherwiſe then by a Biſhop, as we ſee frequently practiſed in Territoryes of good extent. It was then a hard ſhift out of a doctrine not true, by inference to proue a poynt ſo preiudiciall to Catholikes, as <hi>M. Doctours</hi> concluſion was. At leaſt it cannot be denyed, but <hi>Sotus</hi> his wordes, by this diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, appeare to be obſcure, and therfore could yield but vncertayne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe to <hi>M. Doctours</hi> hard aſſertion.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Concerning <hi>Bannez,</hi> ſee the <hi>Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour n.</hi> 11. who truly affirmed, that he made nothinge for <hi>M. Doctour.</hi> When he teacheth, that the Pope cannot remoue Biſhops from a <hi>great part</hi> of the Church, he vnderſtandes as we commonly call one thing, <hi>a great part</hi> of another, as certainly one countrey is not a great part of the Catholicke church, which extendeth it ſelfe as farre as the world, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, if in ſuch a countrey, there be no more Catholickes, then are in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 28. doth his vtmoſt to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16320:26"/>proue, that by diuine Law, euery particular Church muſt haue a Biſhop, and when all comes to all, the point is reduced to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Confirmation.</hi> But this is a weake ground, to oblige Catholickes to receaue a Biſhop, with increaſe of perſecution. For firſt a Biſhop, for <hi>Confirmation</hi> only, can be no more neceſſary, then <hi>Confirmation</hi> it ſelfe, which is not a Sacrament of neceſſity, and according to all Deuines, may be omitted without ſinne, when commodiouſly it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had; which certainly happeneth, when a Biſhop cannot come into the Country, but accompanyed with addition to a grieuous perſecution. 2. That Sacrament may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by a Prieſt, with commiſsion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope. 3. Although it were neceſſarily to be adminiſtred by a Biſhop yet it requireth, only Epiſcopal Order, with voluntary iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as Prieſts in England haue ouer their Penitents. 4. It requireth not a Biſhop belonging to <hi>England,</hi> or reſiding in that Kingdome. 5. <hi>M. Doctour</hi> alleadgeth the diuine precept, of hauing Biſhops in euery notable part of the Church, as a diſtinct ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from his other reaſon of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> as may be ſeene in his <hi>chap. 14. n. 4.</hi> and the <hi>Replyer</hi> doth not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently defend <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> by flying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one to the other. The point touching <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> belongs to the next <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. All that he hath <hi>n. 29. 30. 31. 32.</hi> is the very ſame with the obiections, of the <hi>Jnquiſition Sect. 6.</hi> and is anſwered by the <hi>Qualificatour,</hi> in the ſame ſection ſo cleerly, as I need adde no more.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16320:26"/>16. By the ſame forme of argument, wherby <hi>M. Doctour</hi> proued the neceſſity of a Biſhop, in euery Countrey of exent, the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> ſayd, it might be proued; That in euery Countrey, Religious Inſtitute is to be maintayned, becauſe the Pope is obliged to conſerue it, in the whole Church of God. But there is no more reaſon of one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, then of another: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is to be man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in euery Countrey. To this the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> anſwereth <hi>n. 33. 34.</hi> Firſt, that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> can not fynd out a diuine precept, obliging the Pope to admit any Religious Order, as he is bound to giue Biſhops to the Church. But I belieue if he conſider the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter better, he will not aduenture to ſay; That the Pope can depriue the Church of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Eſtate, Inſtituted by our Sauiour Chriſt, whoſe Councels faithfull people can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, without iniury, be vniuerſally hindred to follow. Secondly, he anſwereth; That he hath proued it to be of the diuine law, that euery notable part of the Church haue a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; wheras no Religious Order is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary by the diuine law in euery notable part of the Church. But he neyther hath proued, what he aſſumeth as proued, nor doth he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the forme of <hi>Nicholas Smiths</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was the ſame with that, which <hi>M. Doctour</hi> vſed to proue the neceſſity of a Biſhop in <hi>England.</hi> And ſo when the <hi>Replyer</hi> biddeth the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> make what he can of this anſwere; till he giue a better, this vſe any man may make of it, to ſay with truth, that it maketh nothing for <hi>M. Doctours</hi> reaſon,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16320:27"/>but only to ſhew the inſufficiency of it.</p>
            <p n="17">17. No leſſe deficient is he, in ſatisfying another forme of Argument, brought by <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> in reſemblance of that of <hi>M. Doctours:</hi> It is not of the diuine law, to haue a Biſhop in euery particular Dioceſſe of <hi>England:</hi> But, if we reſpect the diuine law, there is no more reaſon of one Dioceſſe then another; <hi>Ergo,</hi> all the Dioceſſes of <hi>England</hi> may be gouerned without a Biſhop. And the ſame argument may be made of all other Countreys. To this forme of argument the <hi>Replyer</hi> anſwereth; That there is more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of a Biſhop in a whole Countrey, then in euery particular Dioceſſe, which was not the queſtion, but whether it was not as good a forme of argument, as that which <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> vſed. I omit to note, that the <hi>Replyer</hi> miſciteth the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> who ſayd not, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> confeſſed, that a particular Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe may be without a Biſhop, but ſpake reſeruedly, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſeemed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it; which is true, becauſe he ſtil expreſly declared himſelfe to ſpeake, of a notable great part of the Church. Howſoeuer, the thinge it ſelfe is true, that the Pope is not, by diuine law, obliged to giue a Biſhop, to euery place capable of one, as we ſee often practiſed. Would <hi>M. Doctour</hi> perhaps, haue in <hi>England,</hi> as many Biſhops, as there be Dioceſſes? What miſtery may there be, that the <hi>Replier</hi> doth ſo purpoſly conceale <hi>M. Doctours</hi> opinion in this point? To confirme more, what <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> ſayd, I argue thus in <hi>M. Doctours</hi> forme. It is not of the diuine
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16320:27"/>law, that <hi>England</hi> haue a Biſhop: properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Biſhop of <hi>England,</hi> or of any Dioceſſe therin: But there is no more reaſon of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> then of other Countreyes. <hi>Ergo</hi> all other Countreys may be without a Biſhop, properly called Biſhop of ſuch Countreys, or of any Dioceſſe therin. This is <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> forme of argument, and yet the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence cannot by any Catholicke be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned.</p>
            <p n="18">18. At length the <hi>Replyer n.</hi> 36. agreeth with vs, that it muſt be left to the ſupreme Paſtors diſcretion, whether the diuine law obligeth a Countrey to haue a Biſhop, in this, or that circumſtance, and ſo <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> and the <hi>Replyer</hi> might haue ſpared their paynes, in prouing that <hi>England</hi> muſt haue a Biſhop, becauſe there is a diuine law, that euery great part of the Church, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue <hi>England</hi> to be, haue its proper Biſhop. Yet I cannot approue his other ſaying, that when we demaund any thing, there is more reaſon to demaund, that which is ordinary, then that which is extraordinary, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>England</hi> may demaund an Ordinary. For the rule of wiſe men ought rather to be, that they demaund, what is moſt ſutable to tyme place, and other Circumſtances, and not what is ordinary, or extraordinary. God grant our caſe of <hi>England,</hi> were not extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, and much different from that of other Catholicke Countreys.</p>
            <p n="19">19. He doth likwiſe not a litle relent, in the ſame <hi>n. 36.</hi> where fynding <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſore preſſed by the <hi>Diſcuſſour n. 15.16.</hi> that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16320:28"/>his arguments, if they paſſe for good, muſt alſo proue, that <hi>Scotland</hi> is obliged to haue its Biſhop, yea that both <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> muſt haue an Ordinary, properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe <hi>Scotland</hi> is a Countrey of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and by the diuine law, beſide the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtour, there muſt be other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naryes, or Eccleſiaſtical Princes in the whole Church, and conſequently (according to the groundes of <hi>M. Doctour</hi> &amp; the <hi>Replyer</hi>) euery notable part of the Church, muſt haue a Biſhop, in that proper ſenſe. To this the <hi>Replyer</hi> anſwereth: If <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> be both notable partes of the Church, both ought to haue, by the diuine law, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Biſhop, be he Ordinary, or Delegate. If? Doth he beginne to doubt, whether they be both notable parts of the Church, or Churches of extent? Or can he aſſigne vs a diuine law for <hi>England,</hi> not for <hi>Scotland?</hi> I ſee, he may in tyme accorde with <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> whome ere while he ſo much taxed, for ſaying, that <hi>England,</hi> as now thinges ſtand, is no notable part of Gods whole Church. Moreuer, the diuine law, of hauing ſome Biſhops in the Church, is of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes in an ordinary manner, not of Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates; and therfore if Delegates ſuffice in <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> it is a ſigne the diuine law doth not oblige in thoſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys; and if by Biſhops Delegates the diuine law be fulfilled, it may be fulfilled by Prieſts De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates, for as much as concerneth iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p n="20">20. I will anſwere his <hi>n. 37.</hi> only by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16320:28"/>what he leaueth out in citing the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſours</hi> wordes <hi>q. 7. n. 15.</hi> I (ſayth <hi>Nicholas Smith) would most willingly ſpend my bloud, for purchaſing of tymes, ſutable with the enioying a Catholicke Bishop in England.</hi> Where the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> leaueth off, and maketh a longe need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe deſcant vpon a poynt euery playne, if he had added the wordes, immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, namely <hi>(indued with as much autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as any particular Bishop in the whole Church of God.)</hi> Which tymes almighty God grant vs with ſpeed, if ſo it be his diuine will.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The confutation of <hi>M. Doctours</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, drawne from the <hi>Affrican</hi> Church, is by the <hi>Replyer</hi> anſwered, with a gentle, &amp; implicit conceſſion, of all that the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> had obiected. For omitting all particulars, he telleth vs, that they were alleadged by <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> only to ſhew their zeale, and great deſire of a Biſhop. But ſeeing <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> did ſhew, that there was no parity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their caſe and ours, and alſo that the <hi>Affrican</hi> Biſhops, did not approue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples zeale, but rather gaue a preſident, that zeale is to be tempered with diſcretion, the ſayd examples, were neyther rightly allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> nor is <hi>M. Doctour</hi> well defended by the <hi>Replyer.</hi> As farre as <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> will giue way, Engliſh Catholickes will yielde to none, in zeale to haue a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="question">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16320:29"/>
            <head>THE IIII. QVESTION. <hi>Whether a Countrey, although the Perſecution should be increaſed, by occaſion of hauing a Bishop, could refuſe one, if it were only for the Sacrament of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Replyer</hi> chargeth <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> for changing the queſtion, as if he had impoſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> M. <hi>Doctour</hi> that he taught, euery man in particular to be obliged, to hazard goods, liberty, &amp; lyfe, for enioying <hi>Confirmation,</hi> wheras M. <hi>Doctour</hi> only ſpake of perſecution in general. But <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer impoſed vpon M. <hi>Doctour</hi> that ſaying, nor do the <hi>Diſcuſsours</hi> wordes, alleadged by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> import any ſuch matter, but he euer ſpake of perſecution, to be increaſed by the comming of a Biſhop, which might as well fall vpon this, as that man, and in that ſenſe, euery one in particular, might feare it for himſelfe. Yet <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, whither ſome in particular, might not, without danger, receaue <hi>Confirmation,</hi> ſuppoſing we had a Biſhop, which touched not the queſtion in hand. For certayne it is, that <hi>Confirmation</hi> cannot be ſayd, to be had commodiouſly, (which was the poynt that made moſt for the purpoſe) if it cannot be receaued, without a Biſhop, whoſe very comminge, was ſuppoſed to cauſe increaſe of perſecution, to Catholickes in generall; which is more conſiderable, then if it were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16320:29"/>certayne, that by his comming, ſome one man only were to ſuffer domage, as <hi>Nicolas Smith n. 17.</hi> ſayd truly, but is not rightly taken by the <hi>Replyer n. 5.</hi> And by this is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his long diſcourſe <hi>n.</hi> 29. 30. <hi>31. 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His arguments, concerning <hi>Perfect Christianity</hi> are examined in the <hi>Qualification ſect. 4.</hi> where it is explicated, in what ſenſe we are by Confirmation, made perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and is demonſtrated, that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer denyed it, in the ſenſe in which the holy Fathers ſpake.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Likewiſe the <hi>Qualificatour ſect. 3.</hi> ſheweth that <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> concerning the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>S. Clements</hi> Epiſtles, hath no more, yea leſſe, then is to be read in <hi>Bellarmine, Poſſoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> and <hi>Baronius.</hi> And further ſheweth, that <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> doth not reiect them, as Heretickes do; and laſtly, that the ſayd Epiſtles make nothing agaynſt the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That which <hi>M. Doctour</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> ſhould haue done, and by <hi>Nicolas Smith n. 16.</hi> were vrged to do, ſhould haue bin, to prooue that to be perfect Chriſtians in the Fathers ſenſe, was of ſo great neceſsity, that for attayning thereof, Catholickes ought to endure perſecution: But this neyther <hi>M. Doctour</hi> did performe, nor doth the <hi>Replyer,</hi> as much as take notice of. And truly in what ſenſe ſoeuer we take <hi>S. Clement,</hi> and other Fathers, or Councels, teaching, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Confirmation we are not perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, nor properly Chriſtians, yea not Chriſtians at all (for ſo ſome ſpeake) it is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16320:30"/>allwayes to be vnderſtood, if that Sacrament be omitted voluntarily, when it may be had, otherwiſe we may be perfect Chriſtians; that is, it ſhall not be imputed to vs, that we are not perfect Chriſtians, but God will ſupply that want by other meanes. As if a <hi>Cathecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> belieuing perfectly in Chriſt, dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Baptiſme yet with intenſe Contrition, not hauing poſſibility to be actually bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, he may be ſayd to dye a Chriſtian, yea a good, and holy Chriſtian; becauſe the want of Baptiſmal Character is not imputed to him (as it would to one, who by his fault had omitted it) in regard he wantes it, only <hi>negatiue</hi> not <hi>priuatiue;</hi> he hath it not, yet wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts it not, by reaſon in that caſe he was not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue it in act, but only in effectuall deſire. As after Baptiſme, remiſſion of deadly ſins, the proper effect of the Sacrament of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> may be obtayned by <hi>Contrition,</hi> as it includes a deſire of that Sacrament; which deſire in that caſe, is reputed for the act. This is a cleere explication, of thoſe words left out by <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> in citing <hi>S. Clement (ſi non neceſſitate &amp;c. Jf he shall remaine ſo, not vpon neceſsity, but by careleſneſſe, or volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily.)</hi> Which were wordes of chiefe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when we diſputed of omitting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, not careleſly, but for iuſt feare of perſecution, becauſe we are not bound to be perfect Chriſtians, in that peculiar ſenſe, with ſo great domage; nor will the want of ſuch perfection, in that caſe, be imputed to vs, but God of his goodneſſe, will be ready to ſupply, the effect of Confirmation, for as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16320:30"/>much as concerneth actuall grace, and aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without the Character; becauſe, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that ſuppoſition, of perſecution to be increaſed, there is a morall kind of impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to receaue it. By which obſeruation, falleth downe all that the <hi>Replyer</hi> obiects, <hi>n.</hi> 16. about <hi>Baptiſme</hi> not actually receaued, and <hi>Confirmation n. 22.</hi> and both <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Confirmation n. 23.</hi> as the Reader wil perceaue, by applying to his obiections, what euen now I haue noted. For we do not ſay, that without vnction one can be annoynted, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be omitted vpon neceſsity, but only, that the want of it ſhall not be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yea ſhall be otherwiſe ſupplyed; and the like I ſay of <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> whereas if vnction be omitted voluntarily, the party ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted neither Sacramentally, by the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, nor Equiualently by other helpes from God, and ſo he ſhall deſerue to be truly called not a perfect Chriſtian. By the way I obſerue, that <hi>n. 22.</hi> he confoundeth two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct anſweres giuen by the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> by which meanes it is eaſy to make a ſhew of difficulty, or to confute any two opinions, or anſwers giuen as different, yet both as probable, as Schollers dayly giue diuers probable anſwers to one difficulty, which taken togeather cannot both ſubſiſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite different, or contrary; and if one be determinatly imbraced as true, the other muſt be relinquiſhed as not true, all-though it may ſtill retaine its probability, &amp; to ſome other man perhaps ſeeme alſo more true. The <hi>Qualificatour Sect. 7. n. 17.</hi> ſheweth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16320:31"/>that other Catholike Authors, might well leaue out thoſe wordes of <hi>S. Clement (if not by neceſſity &amp;c.)</hi> becauſe they treated not the caſe of perſecution, of which <hi>M. Doctour</hi> did ſpeake, and ſo they had no like obligation to cite thoſe wordes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But (ſayth the <hi>Replyer</hi>) rather <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Smith</hi> falſifyeth <hi>S. Clement,</hi> whoſe words are theſe: <hi>All therfore must make hast, without delay to be regenerated to God, and then to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Bishop &amp;c. And when he shall be regenerated by water, and afterward confirmed by the Bishop, with the ſeauenfolde grace of the ſpirit, for otherwiſe he cannot be a perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, nor haue place amongſt the perfect, if he ſo remaine, not by neceſsity but by careleſneſſe, or volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarily.</hi> Where the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> left out theſe wordes <hi>(nor haue place amongst the perfect,)</hi> which he thinkes to be of great importance, and to ſignify that he cannot be admitted to the ſacred Euchariſt, nor to the ranke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are admitted to it, if not by neceſſity, but voluntarily he ſhall ſo remayne. For if by neceſsity, the party baptized wanted Confirmation, he might be admitted to the Euchariſt. But I am not of his opinion that thoſe wordes were of importance, and dare aſſure him in the <hi>Diſcuſſours</hi> behalfe, that he neuer dreamed of any myſtery, which could moue him, purpoſely to omit them. It is very ſtrang that the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> ſhould be blamed, for omitting only the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned words, and <hi>M. Doctour</hi> excuſed, although he left out the very ſame words, &amp; alſo the words that followed <hi>(Jf not by neceſſity &amp;c.)</hi> Are you ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16320:31"/>vnfriendly to <hi>Nieolas Smith,</hi> that vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to eſpy one omiſsion in him, you are content to acknowledge a double one in <hi>M. Doctour?</hi> Your ſelfe muſt ſatisfy for <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> and anſwere your own arguments <hi>n. 22.23.</hi> wherewith you ſo much preſſed the <hi>Diſcuſsour;</hi> for in S. <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> theſe words <hi>(If not by neceſſity, but by &amp;c.)</hi> are refered to both the precedet clauſes <hi>(he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be a perfect Christia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)</hi> &amp; to the other <hi>(nor haue place amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the perfect)</hi> as appeareth by the coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>(nor)</hi> &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Clement</hi> ſignifyeth, that he cannot be a perfect Chriſtian, if not by neceſsity, but voluntarily he omit Confirmation. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe wordes, <hi>nor haue place amongst the perfect,</hi> eyther are but a repetition or expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the former, or if they ſignify ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what els, they haue no more reference to the wordes <hi>(If not by neceſſity &amp;c.)</hi> then the other clauſe <hi>(he cannot be a perfect Christian)</hi> which as I explicated aboue, ſignify, that the want of perfect chriſtianity, acquired by actuall vnction, and by receauing a military Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, ſhall not be imputed to him, but that God wil ſupply the grace of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> by other meanes, if indeed he want it vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as they do, who are depriued of it, vpon iuſt feare of perſecution. The <hi>Replyers</hi> explication of theſe words <hi>(nor haue place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the perfect)</hi> muſt be reiected by himſelf for he teacheth, that there was in theſe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, an Eccleſiaſticall cuſtome of being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, before one receaued the B. Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, and conſequently it was not lawfull to do it, except in ſome caſe of neceſsity; for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16320:32"/>example, at the houre of death, when the diuine precept of communicating did oblige and as it were drowne the Eccleſiaſticall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept; in which caſe the perſon vnconfirmed was bound to receaue the B. Sacrament, whether he had omitted Confirmation by neceſsity, or voluntarily; only he was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue Contrition for his former omiſsion. And therfore the <hi>Replyer</hi> cannot aſsigne any caſe, in theſe tymes, of diſparity betwixt him, who had omitted Confirmation volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, and him who had omitted it vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity; becauſe when ſuch a neceſsity did vrge, both of them might, and ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the Bleſſed Sacrament, (and ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Replyers</hi> explication haue place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the perfect;) and when no ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity did happen, neyther of them could receaue the B. Euchariſt: and therfore as I ſayd, the <hi>Replyers</hi> explication cannot ſubſiſt with his owne grounds. Moreouer, <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> had reaſon to thinke it a hard doctrine that without Confirmation, we ſhall be ſure to want ſuch a perfection in our Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as we ſhould be obliged vnder ſinne, to ſuffer a generall perſecution, for redeeming the want of ſuch a perfection. For to that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere purpoſe <hi>M. Doctour</hi> alleadged S. <hi>Clement</hi> and in that ſenſe <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> had reaſon to deny, that without Confirmation we could not be perfect Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="6">6. What he ſayth <hi>n. 27.</hi> that Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a perfecting vnction, is not againſt the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> who neuer denyed it, nor euer treated, whether <hi>S. Denis</hi> in his 5. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16320:32"/>ſpake of Confirmation; but only ſayth, and proueth, that in the ſayd Chapter, he ſpeaketh alſo of oyle vſed in Baptiſme, and that therfore out of ſuch generall ſpeaches alone, <hi>M. Doctour</hi> could not inferre any thing peculiar to Confirmation. See the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs. n. 17.</hi> which in this point is cleare inough.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Reader muſt vnderſtand with circumſpection, the <hi>Replyers</hi> doctrine <hi>n.</hi> 10. That God obligeth himſelfe, to giue the ſpeciall grace of Confirmation (to profeſſe our faith) to ſuch as receaue it. For this muſt be vnderſtoode, if Perſons <hi>Confirmed,</hi> do on their part concur with Gods grace, mouing, and inciting them, to the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his commandments, &amp; performance of other good workes, according to his inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirations, beſides the only receauing of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation. Otherwiſe he may iuſtly deny them particular efficacious grace, permitting them to fayle in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of their faith, whiles others, by humble frequentation of other Sacraments, &amp; diligence in good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, do by thoſe meanes ſupply the want of Confirmation, and remayne conſtant, in the confeſſion fo their faith. Likwiſe, wheras <hi>n.</hi> 40. &amp; in other places, he teacheth, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation is the ordinary meanes to get gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, for confeſſing our faith; If he vnderſtand that all other meanes are extraordinary, his doctrine is not true. For otherwiſe <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> were a neceſſary meanes, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith, and for ſaluation; ſo as no man vnconfirmed, could without mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle confeſſe his faith, although he inculpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:16320:33"/>omit <hi>Confirmation,</hi> &amp; otherwiſe keepe the commandments, frequent Sacraments, be aſſiduous in prayer, &amp; feruent in all other good works: which no man can defend. If, by ordinary meanes, he vnderſtand a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ordayned to giue grace, for the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our faith, the doctrine is good. But thence doth not follow, that other meanes alſo may not ſuffice, for the Confeſſion of our faith, becauſe the ſame end may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by different meanes. See the <hi>Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation Sect. 4. n. 7.</hi> Neuertheleſſe, if in ſome particular caſe, one did in Conſcience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe that without Confirmation, he ſhould not haue ſtrength to profeſſe his faith, ſuch an one were bound to receaue that Sacrament, as <hi>Conick</hi> related by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer n. 41.</hi> affirmeth. But this is <hi>per accidens,</hi> as one may ſome tyme be obliged to faſt, or vndertake other corporall auſterityes, to confeſſe, receaue the B. Sacrament, or ſome ſuch pious worke, if he were in Conſcience perſwaded, that without ſuch a particular determinate meanes, he could not ouercome ſome temptation.</p>
            <p n="8">8. From the 33. to the <hi>38. number</hi> he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth to defend <hi>M. Doctours</hi> ſaying, That <hi>Euſebius</hi> recounteth, <hi>Nouatus</hi> to haue fallen, for want of Confirmation. Firſt, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that indeed <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth not ſay ſo in expreſſe tearmes: <hi>Ergo</hi> do I inferre, <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> ſayd not well, that <hi>Nouatus</hi> fell for want of Confirmation, <hi>as Euſebius hath remarked,</hi> for ſo, he ſpeaketh in his <hi>Epistle n. 18.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he telleth vs, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16320:33"/>ſo much. But <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſayth more: and I deny, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate it, then by ſaying, that he wanted the grace of Confirmation; as likwiſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth, that he was ambitious, with many other crimes. And indeed his ſchiſme, and hereſy may be aſcribed to his ambition, and oppoſition to <hi>Cornelius</hi> for the Popedome, rather then to any thing elſe. For Hereſy, and ſchiſme, are the immediate broode of pryde, and ambition. Thirdly he ſayth, that at leaſt it may be probably inferred out of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that <hi>Nouatus</hi> fell for want of <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> But heere we talke not of inferences, but whether, or no, <hi>Euſebius</hi> do affirme it? Neyther doth it follow; He fell, and wanted <hi>Confirmation: Ergo,</hi> he fell for want of <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> For as he wanted <hi>Confirmation,</hi> ſo was he ambitious, and loaden with other ſinnes. Yet <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> out of reſpect to that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſayd, it might well be, he fell for want of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> as alſo it may be, that he fell, both for his ſinne of neglecting, and contemning that Sacrament, and ioyntly for other his groſſe enormityes. Only I ſtill deny, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſayth, he fell for want of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation. His laſt anſwere is, that others before <hi>M. Doctour</hi> haue written out of <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> that <hi>Nouatus</hi> fell for want of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is to confeſſe that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> taketh his arguments vpon truſt, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerning the obligation of afflicted Catholickes, to endure a heauyer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vpon truſt from Authors, who treated not that particular, important Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16320:34"/>which <hi>M. Doctour</hi> was to proue: and this is ſo much the more to be wondred at, becauſe, the example of <hi>Nouatus,</hi> is by him diuers tymes repeated, as if it were ſome Maiſter-peece, and yet finally the <hi>Replyer</hi> confeſſeth, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> tooke it from the notes of the <hi>Rhemes Testament,</hi> granting therby, that for alleadging ſome other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, to the ſame effect, he is obliged to the <hi>Replyer,</hi> and ſo not thoſe Authors, but only the <hi>Rhemes Testament</hi> can excuſe <hi>M. Doctour.</hi> But indeed, neyther thoſe <hi>Venerable Authors</hi> of the ſayd notes, nor other Catholicke Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, can giue excuſe for his miſalleadging <hi>Euſebius.</hi> For out of <hi>Euſebius</hi> they cleerly proue againſt hereticques, that Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Sacrament, and a thing not to be contemned, becauſe for want of it <hi>Nouatus</hi> receaued not the holy Ghoſt, and was by <hi>Cornelius</hi> condemned for neglect to receaue it. All which <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth in expreſſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes relate, and ſo makes good, what Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Authors intend to proue agaynſt Hereticques, although indeed he ſay not, that <hi>Nouatus fell for want of Confirmation,</hi> which made not much to the purpoſe of the ſayd Catholicke Authors. But the ſtrengh of <hi>M. Doctours</hi> argument, doth wholy rely, vpon <hi>Euſebius</hi> his affirming, that <hi>Nouatus</hi> actually fell for want of <hi>Confirmation.</hi> For it was to proue, that without Confirmation, <hi>if one fall not, others probably will,</hi> as (ſayth he) <hi>Nouatus did for want of it.</hi> Thus he ſpeaketh <hi>Chap. 14. n. 8.</hi> and in other places. And it had binne a ſtrange argument, to ſay: <hi>Nouatus</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:16320:34"/>fell not: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Engliſh Catholickes by his example, may feare to fall.</p>
            <p n="9">9. But what if <hi>M. Doctour</hi> do alſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the <hi>Rhemes Testament,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Replyer</hi> in lieu of apologizing for <hi>M. Doctour</hi> his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alleadging <hi>Euſebius,</hi> be put to defend both <hi>M. Doctour</hi> and himſelf, for miſtaking thoſe very notes of the <hi>Rhemes Testament?</hi> I belieue it will proue ſo. We muſt therefore diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh a double fall of <hi>Nouatus.</hi> The one, when for feare of perſecution he denyed himſelfe to be Prieſt, refuſing to helpe ſome Chriſtians in neceſſity, and hazard, for which and the like occaſions, agaynſt feare in time of Perſecution, <hi>Confirmation</hi> is peculiarly ordayned. His other fall, was into ſchiſme, oppoſition to <hi>Cornelius</hi> for the Popedome, and hereſy. This ſecond lapſe was not cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by feare of perſecution, but proceeded from pryde, ambition, and neglect, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which in him was eyther a formall act of hereſy, or a diſpoſition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his ſoule for a fall into further ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and hereſy: neyther did he in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kind of fall deny himſelfe to be Prieſt, but rather ſought to vſurpe the higheſt Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſthood; and the perſecution tended not to driue men into ſchiſme or hereſy, but wholy to bereaue them of Chriſtianity. Now <hi>M. Doctour</hi> muſt vnderſtand, that <hi>Nouatus</hi> his fall, or denying himſelfe to be Prieſt, in the foreſayd circumſtances, for feare of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, happened, becauſe he wanted <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> whereas the <hi>Rhemes Testament</hi> ſayth no ſuch matter, but ſpeakes only of his fall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16320:35"/>to hereſy, and of his contempt of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo makes nothing for <hi>M. Doctours</hi> purpoſe. Let vs heare the words of the <hi>Rhemes Testament,</hi> cited by the <hi>Replyer n. 36. Neuer none denied, or contemned the Sacrament of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and holy Chriſme, but knowne Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes.</hi> S. Cornelius <hi>that Bleſſed Martyr ſo much prayſed of</hi> S. Cyprian, <hi>affirmeth that</hi> Nouatus <hi>fell to hereſy, for that he had not receaued the holy Ghost, by the conſignation of a Bishop, whome all the</hi> Nouatians <hi>did follow, neuer vſing that holy Chriſme.</hi> What is heere for <hi>M. Doctours</hi> purpoſe concerning the fall of <hi>Nouatus</hi> for feare of perſecution? Perhaps, if he had bin more perſecuted, he had not binne ſo ſubiect to ambition, and prone to ſchiſme, &amp; hereſy. <hi>Bayus</hi> likwiſe, cited by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Nouatus</hi> his propenſion to hereſy, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes no more in excuſe of <hi>M. Doctour</hi> then the <hi>Rhemes Testament</hi> did. Beſides, the <hi>Replier</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth no anſwere at all, to <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, that the caſe of <hi>Nouatus,</hi> was infinitly different, from that of our Catholickes in <hi>England,</hi> although it were granted that <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatus</hi> indeed fell for want of Confirmation, which he omitted not vpon iuſt cauſe, but neglected, and contemned, whome all the <hi>Nouatians</hi> did follow, neuer vſing that holy Chriſme, as euen now we haue heard out of the <hi>Rhemes Testament.</hi> The <hi>Replyer</hi> then is many wayes deficient in this poynt. I could adde, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> cites <hi>Euſebius</hi> more then once, very particularly, <hi>lib. 6. Chap. 33.</hi> alias <hi>34.</hi> wheras the <hi>Rhemes Testament</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Chap. 35.</hi> ſo as it is not very obuious,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16320:35"/>how <hi>M. Doctour</hi> tooke his relation from thoſe notes, ſeeing with ſuch particularity, he cites <hi>Euſebius</hi> differently from them. But I will not be ſo minute with the <hi>Replyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. In his <hi>number 40.</hi> he ſayth, that many who may commodiouſly receaue Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue right to receaue it, and that the reſt of Catholickes cannot, for a generall perſecution, depriue them of that right. But this at the moſt proueth, that if once we haue a Biſhop, thoſe who may commodiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue Confirmation, cannot be hindred, but not that they ſhould be wronged, if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for auoyding a generall perſecution, and prouiding for their owne indemnity ſhould, by lawfull, and orderly meanes, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the comming of a Biſhop. Rather, the particular good of ſome, muſt giue place to the generall harme of others. Beſydes, the danger being generall, euery one might feare that it would fall vpon himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="11">11. To proue, that a Biſhop cannot be refuſed, he bringeth this reaſon <hi>n.</hi> 43. It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, but that Chriſtians are more able, and likely to profeſſe their fayth, with the Sacrament of Confirmation, then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and that more in a Countrey perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are like to ſtand to the Profeſsion of their faith, with this Sacrament, then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; <hi>Ergo,</hi> in a Countrey perſecuted, and deſtitute of this Sacrament, many do fall, who otherwiſe would ſtand; and for euery one that ſtandeth, perhaps twenty will fall. God forbid. Hitherto we haue not, nor I hope euer ſhall behold ſo twentifold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16320:36"/>in our glorious Catholickes. To your argument, I anſwere. No doubt, out conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Sacrament of Confirmation in it ſelfe, Chriſtians are more able to profeſſe their faith with it, then without it yet if we ſuppoſe, that by the very hauing of it, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution muſt be increaſed, ſome will be of opinion, that more might be in danger to fall by reaſon of that increaſe of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then in calmer tymes, although they wanted Confirmation. And if the <hi>Antoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> be granted without diſtinction, yet it would not inferre the neceſſity of a Biſhop, with increaſe of Perfecution. No doubt, but by often receauing the Sacrament of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and the moſt B. Sacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, for example, euery eyght dayes, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are more enabled, to profeſſe their faith then without them. Wil therfore the <hi>Replyer,</hi> impoſe vpon Catholickes, an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of frequenting thoſe Sacraments, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery eyght dayes, euen with increaſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution? Which inſtance will be of more force, if one affirme (as I doubt not but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers will) that by humble, and diligent fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting thoſe two Sacraments, perſons who without their fault want Confirmation, may be thought to haue greater ſtrength, for profeſſing their faith, then ſuch as haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued Confirmation but are remiſſe in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting thoſe other two Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Yet M. <hi>Doctour,</hi> and the <hi>Replyer,</hi> come ſhort of their intent, vnleſſe they can further proue, that perſecution is to be vndergone, not only for enioying Confirmation, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16320:36"/>alſo, for the <hi>aſſurednes</hi> or <hi>vudoubtednes</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro by hauing it from a Biſhop, as I touched in the firſt <hi>Question n.</hi> 2. and the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>n.</hi> 8. and the <hi>Qualificator Sect.</hi> 6 <hi>n.</hi> 21.22. Which poynt, &amp; diuers others in this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion treated by <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> are omirted by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> as may be ſeene in the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="question">
            <head>THE V. QVESTION. <hi>Concerning</hi> M. <hi>Doctours Compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Bishops, inferior Pastours, and Religtous men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. IN this Queſtion, the <hi>Replyer</hi> extendeth himſelfe eyther in prouing thinges ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly granted and taught by <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> as that the ſtate of a Biſhop, is higher then that of a Religious man; or els in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning <hi>Nicholas Smith,</hi> as if he had ſayd, what he neuer ſayd nor thought, &amp; therfore we may be more breife in returning him an anſwere. Only, I muſt renew my firſt requeſt to the Reader that if he fynd any ſeeming difficulty, obiected by the <hi>Reptyer,</hi> he will be pleaſed to peruſe <hi>Nicholas Smiths</hi> wordes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſpend his iudgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Qualificator Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 16.17.18. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth the obiections of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> and <hi>Reply</hi> agaynſt <hi>Nicholas Smiths</hi> ſaying, that the ſtate of a Biſhop doth ſuppoſe, but not giue perfection which is the expreſſe doctrine of <hi>Suarez</hi> &amp; common among Deuines. The ſtate of a Biſhop is not only different, but alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16320:37"/>from Epiſcopal Order, or Character, as is manifeſt in a Biſhop confirmed not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, who hath the ſtate, not the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Biſhop. <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, that Epiſcopall conſecration confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth grace, but only that Epiſcopall ſtate of it ſelfe yieldeth meanes to acquire perſonall perfection. By this is anſwered what the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plier</hi> obiecteth <hi>n. 14.15.16.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To proue that in ſome caſe, an Oath not to be Religious, is not wicked, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth <hi>n. 26.</hi> the command of the ſea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke, that all thoſe, who will enioy the benefit of the Popes Seminaries, do ſweare that they will be Prieſts, and will not enter into any Religious Order, or Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without licence of the Pope, vnleſſe they firſt labour in the Miſsion, the ſpace of three yeares. I anſwere <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſpake of an abſolute Vow (or oath) not to enter into Religion, which certaynly is inualid, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, and may be well tearmed wicked. For what greater diſordination can there be in mans will, then deliberatly to ſweare, or vow, that he will reſiſt almighty God, inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring him to follow thoſe Counſels, which were recommended by the Sauiour of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? The oath alleadged by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> is as it were conditionall (not without the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes leaue, or the leaue of his Nuntio, for ſo is the oath now conceaued) and temporary (for the ſpace of three yeares.) The reaſon of difference is, becauſe a vow is inualid, if it be <hi>impeditiuum maioris boni,</hi> incompatible with a greater good, as a temporary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16320:37"/>vow is not. For, not to enter into Religion without leaue, or not for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne tyme, doth not abſolutly hinder en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into Religion. If one vow to make a pilgrimage, or to performe ſome ſuch pious worke, the vow is valid, although the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof, do for a tyme, hinder the Pilgrims entring into Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neyther doth it follow, that therfore a Pilgrimage, is an act more perfect, then the imbracing of a Religious lyfe, taking holy Orders &amp;c. Or that the Vocation of ſtudents in the Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, is more perfect then the ſtate of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop out of England, which yet Seminariſts, by reaſon of their oath to go into England, cannot imbrace without leaue, at leaſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe firſt they ſatisfy their dath, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into England. Or that the ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or Vocation of Seminary Prieſts is more or leſſe perfect, by the expiring, or not expiring of three yeares, after which tyme, ſeeing all may freely enter into Religion, euen in <hi>England,</hi> it is a ſigne, that Religious ſtate, all things conſidered, is to be preferred.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Without any neceſſity, he endeauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to proue, that in caſe of neceſſity of the church, when it cannot be otherwiſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, a vow to accept a Biſhoprike is lawfull, of which <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> did not diſpute, but only ſayd in generall that a Vow not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a Biſhopricke is lawfull, which no man can deny, vnleſſe he will oppoſe himſelfe to all thoſe Popes, who haue approued the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the ſociety of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> And thoſe very words, which the <hi>Replyer n. 32.</hi> without cauſe,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16320:38"/>noteth <hi>Nicholas Smiths</hi> to haue left out of <hi>S. Thomas 2.2. q. 185. a.</hi> 1. <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe in a manifest, &amp; imminent neceſſity)</hi> confirm what <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſayd, that according to <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> it ſeemeth preſumption to deſire a Biſhopricke, euen for the good of ſoules, namely ſpeaking in generall, and not in ſome particular caſe of neceſsity, which is not very frequent; and who I pray you, will perſuade himſelfe, that he alone is fit for ſo high a ſtate? It is alſo moſt true that, <hi>Valentia</hi> as he is cited by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Smith,</hi> teacheth, that (in generall and abſtracting from particular caſe of neceſsity) to deſire a Biſhopricke, euen for what is beſt in it, is <hi>commonly</hi> a deadly ſinne, although the <hi>Replyer</hi> telleth vs, that <hi>Valentia</hi> thinketh <hi>oftentymes</hi> it is a mortall ſin. Beſides, <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> becauſe he would not medle with that diſpute, knowing there was multiplicity of opinions, after he had alleadged the doctrine of <hi>Valentia</hi> warily, added: <hi>This belongeth not to me to define.</hi> But the <hi>Replyer</hi> willingly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all occaſions to dilate himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His <hi>33.</hi> and <hi>33. numbers,</hi> are employed, by occaſion of a meere partly miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and partly miſciting <hi>Nicolas Smith n. 7.</hi> as the iudicious Reader will fynde, by peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the place in the <hi>Diſcuſſour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. I cannot excuſe the <hi>Replyer</hi> from fault in ſaying <hi>n. 37.</hi> that <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> affirmeth, that a Biſhop <hi>elected,</hi> yea and <hi>confirmed</hi> may marry. <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> his wordes <hi>num. 8.</hi> are theſe: <hi>A Bishop, not in holy Orders, Elected, may lawfully marry, and ſome alſo hold, that a Bishop confirmed may do the ſame; but of this I do
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16320:38"/>not diſpute, yet if he marry, it is valid. Nicholas Smith</hi> then only ſayth, that ſome hold that a Biſhop <hi>confirmed</hi> may marry, which is true, but himſelfe a bſtayneth from that <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. He ſheweth that willingly he would fynde fault with any thing while <hi>n. 36.</hi> he telleth vs, that S. <hi>Thomas 1. 2. q. 104 ar.</hi> 4. as he is cited by <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> ſayth nothing of the Euangelicall Counſels, yet confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth that in his <hi>q.</hi> 108. <hi>ar. 4.</hi> he teacheth that, for which <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> cireth him, namely, that Euangelicall counſels are proper to the new law. The miſciting of the place was an errour of the print, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> might haue ſeene in <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> himſelfe <hi>pag.</hi> 161. where the ſame place of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> is cited aright.</p>
            <p n="8">8. What he writeth <hi>n.</hi> 37 of the knights of <hi>Calatraud &amp;c.</hi> is anſwered by the <hi>Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catour ſect.</hi> 5 <hi>n.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by occaſion of a lyke obiection made by the <hi>Inquiſitor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. His ſaying <hi>n. 41.</hi> that Regulars, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, are not to haue care, or charge of others, but of their owne ſo dies, is eyther a meere Equiuocation, or a doctrine very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, and often confuted by the <hi>Diſcuſſour.</hi> For ſome Regular Prieſts, as Regulars, haue at leaſt as much to do with other mens ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, as ſecular Prieſts, as ſecular, haue; and if Regular Prieſts, be alſo Biſhops, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, they are equall to ſecular Biſhops, &amp; Paſtours. Euery body knowes, that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in generall, is deuided into the Actiue, Contemplatiue, and Mixte lyfe, by which ſuch Religious are obliged to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, both to their owne perfection, and to the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16320:39"/>neyther doth that Mixt kind of lyfe, make a Regular to be Secular; <hi>Ergo</hi> ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulars, euen as they are Regulars, and not ſeculars, are to help others. If ſecular, as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, did artend to the helpe of others then all ſeculars ſhould attend to the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, euen lay men, and women, according to the <hi>Replyers</hi> frequent-manner of diſputing, who is wont to inferre, that if Regulars, as Regulars, were of the Hierarchy (and the ſame may be ſayd of attending to the help of others) then all Regulars, euen lay-Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Religious women, ſhould be of the Hierarchy, and attend to the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If he ſay, that ſecular Prieſts, not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely as Secular, but as Paſtours, attend to the help of others, the ſame ſay I of Regulars if they be made Paſtours. In a word, he ought to compare Regular as Regular, with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar as ſecular, Regular Prieſts, with ſecular Prieſts, Regular Biſhops or Paſtours, with Secular Biſhops or Paſtors, which yet could neuer be obtayned of <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> or the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer.</hi> This manner of vnequall reduplication, <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> reprehended, and not redupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in generall, which euery body ſo well knowes to be vſuall in Schooles, that the <hi>Replyer</hi> need not to haue taken ſo much paynes to proue it <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>n. 1.</hi> I adde, that theſe Religious, who by their Inſtitute, muſt help others, by preaching, adminiſtring Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt alſo by their Religious Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute be Prieſts; but no Secular, preciſely as Secular, is bound to be Prieſt. I ſay preciſely as Secular, for a Secular man, by ſome other
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:16320:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>title, may be obliged to be Prieſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The <hi>Diſcuſsour n. 11.</hi> ſayth that a Biſhop is obliged to enlighten others, &amp; giue his life for his flocke, by iuſtice, in regard of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and honour affoarded him by his flocke, or by the vertue of Fidelity, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of a certayne implicite pact, whereby he obligeth himſelfe, when he is made Biſhop. But Religious men, meerly vpon Charity, or Religion (more noble Vertues, then Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Fidelity) do illuminate others, and aduenture their lyfe for the ſauing of ſoules, obliged, not only by Inſtitute, but alſo by particular vow made to that effect. In which doctrine I can eſpy nothing blame worthy. But the <hi>Replyer n. 43.</hi> ſomety mes citeth theſe wordes of <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> by halfes, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes drawes them to an odious ſenſe, as if Biſhops performed theyr functions mercina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, for honour, and mantenance, or, as if their giuing their lyfe for their ſheepe, were not a worke of Heroicall Charity, or did not require in the Biſhop very great Charity according as our Sauiour ſayd <hi>Joan. 21. Amas me? Paſce ones meas:</hi> wheras the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſayth, that the obligation which Biſhops haue, ariſeth from the vertues of Iuſtice, &amp; Fidelity, although when they giue their life for their flocke, adminiſter Sacraments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they may exerciſe acts of diuers vertues, as Charity, Religion, Fortitude, Patience <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet, as I ſayd, the obligation of thoſe very acts originally proceedeth from the vertues of Iuſtice, and Fidelity; and if another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould chance voluntarily to exerciſe the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16320:40"/>ſame acts, he ſhould not performe them, by the ſame title, and obligation of Iuſtice, by which Biſhops, and Paſtours, are bound to performe them. The ſouldier, by reaſon of his pay, is bound to adueture his lyfe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he may exerciſe acts of Fortitude, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Country, Religion in a pious cauſe, and of other vertues; and yet his obligation to theſe acts of vertues, radically proceedeth from Iuſtice. Neyther can we rightly affirme that he dyeth for his Pay, if he chance to looſe his life, but only that by reaſon of his Pay, in Iuſtice he was bound to dye.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The <hi>Diſcuſſour n. 12.</hi> ſayth: Merit doth not confiſt in office, but in actes thereof. Would any man thinke that in this ſpeach there could be difficulty? Or doth any ſay, that we merit otherwiſe then by actes? Yet the <hi>Replyer</hi> is not pleaſed with it and entreth into a queſtion, which would require a long diſpute, to wit: Whe ther, and how farre the dignity of the perſon, dignifyeth the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? Which Axiome requireth many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations, and explications, as for example; If a Biſhop pay his debts, faſt, or the like, I ſee not why by theſe actes he ſhould merit more, then a priuate Perſon, endued with equall degree of iuſtifying grace, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with equall feruour: neyther can I hold for true, what the <hi>Replyer</hi> ſayth, that the ſame action done by a Regular, and a Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op, are more meritorious in a Biſhop, then in a Regular, not only in reſpect of actions, proper to the State of a Biſhop, but alſo of other actions; vnleſſe the Biſhop be more in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16320:40"/>Gods fauour, and do thoſe actions, with greater perfection. If it were to our preſent purpoſe, one might adde, that in Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall rigour, for the poynt in hand, there is great difference betwixt height of Office, and Dignity of perſon, as our B. Sauiours o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations were of inſinite valew and merit, by reaſon of the dignity of his perſon, not preciſely, and formally by any office.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In his 49. &amp; diuers other numbers he treateth of Secular Curates compared with Religious Prieſts: and no doubt but that ſome things there are, wherein Secular Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates excell a Religious Prieſt, not Curate; which his arguments do proue, &amp; no more. But the Queſtion is, whether all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, a Religious Preiſt be not more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then a ſecular Curate, as <hi>S. Thomas 2.2. q 184. art. 8.</hi> cited by the <hi>Diſcuſſour n. 14.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the Queſtion, and reſolueth it in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Religious Prieſts, as may be ſeene at large in the <hi>Diſcuſſion.</hi> And the <hi>Replyer n. 54.</hi> citeth <hi>Suarez</hi> very imperfectly, that ſo he may ſeeme the more to fauour Secular Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats. For he, <hi>tomo 3. de Relig. lib. 1. cap. 21.</hi> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly prefers Religious Prieſts, teaching that the ſtate of inferiour Paſtors is more perfect only in ſpeculation, not in practice, or <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumquid,</hi> in ſome ſort, <hi>ſeu ex quadam hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, quae moraliter vix adimpletur;</hi> or vpon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſuppoſition which morally ſpeaking is ſcarſely fulfilled. The <hi>Replyers</hi> arguments, That ſecular Curats are Illuminators and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and therefore more perfect then thoſe who are illuminated, do not concerne Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16320:41"/>men in reſpect of whom Secular Curats are no Illuminators. Beſides according to S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> Secular Curates do illuminate not <hi>principaliter,</hi> but with limitation, and ſome participation from the Biſhop, who by office is principall Illuminatour <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Becauſe <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and out of him <hi>M. Doctour</hi> proued, that the ſtate of a Biſhop is more perfect, then that of a Religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe otherwiſe a Religious ma could not be made a Biſhop, for that were <hi>retroſpicere,</hi> to looke back; The <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> by the ſame reaſon proueth, that Religious ſtate is more perfect, then the vocation of a Secular Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, becauſe he may lawfully enter into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The <hi>Replyer</hi> anſwereth that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this is becauſe Religious vocation, is more ſecure then that of a Curate, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more noble. But he doth not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy. For according to this anſwer, a Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Curate might forſake his charge, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a priuate lyfe, attend to himſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obligation to giue account for the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of others, which no doubt were more ſecure; and yet the <hi>Replier</hi> would not excuſe ſuch a one from a <hi>Retroſpection.</hi> Moreouer a Religious ſtate is more ſecure then that of a Biſhop, and yet a Biſhop cannot without leaue enter into Religion, as a Secular Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate may; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is a ſigne that Religious vocation is not only more ſecure, but alſo more perfect then that of a Secular Curate, eſpecially if we adde, what the <hi>Replyer</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to admit, that as the Biſhop is wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; hath a pact with his Church, ſo alſo,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16320:41"/>in proportion, a Curate hath with his charge.</p>
            <p n="14">14. He ſayth <hi>n.</hi> 62. that he will not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret ſo rigorouſly, the words of the Oath, which ſtudents in the Seminaryes do take, as if they were bound to returne into England, ſo often, as the Superiours of the ſayd Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naryes ſhall commaund. Neyther will I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of that poynt, but only ſay, that what ſoeuer perfection they haue by reaſon of that oath, they owe it to Regulars, by whoſe motion the taking of that oath was enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If we reſpect the practiſe, I conceaue that the <hi>Replyer</hi> will find men, more eminent in the Engliſh Cleargy then himſelfe, not to admit of ſo ſtrict an interpretation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that the <hi>Replyer</hi> cannot by vertue of the ſayd oath, place Seminary Prieſts in an immouable ſtate. Without doubt, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men haue an obligation to transferre themſelues into England, as often as their Superiours ſhall ſo commaund. Moreouer ſeeing Regulars in <hi>England,</hi> expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſame dangers, and exerciſe the ſame functions, with Secular Prieſts, and in the ſame manner, namely, by Delegation, and Commiſſion, not as Ordinary Paſtours; it followeth, that in this, Regulars are equall to them, and in reſpect of Religious ſtate ſurpaſſe them, as <hi>Nicholas Smith n. 16.</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and therefore the compariſon betwixt Regular Prieſts, and Secular Curates, can only be in reſpect of ſuch, as are Ordinaryes. Wherfore the <hi>Replyers</hi> ſaying <hi>n. 62.</hi> that the Seminary Prieſts, vnder the Biſhop, is the higheſt calling in the Church of God, is not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16320:42"/>to be approued, if he intend to preferre their calling before all Regulars, who certainly, as Regulars, excell them, as Seculars, and in Calling, ſome are at leaſt equall. I ſay, at leaſt, becauſe there want not Regulars, who are bound by an eſpeciall Vow, to expoſe their liues for the good of ſoules, not only in England, or for a limited tyme, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually, and in whatſoeuer moſt remote place of the world; and euen in that reſpect, although they had no other Vow of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, are in an immoueable ſtate, bynding them to acts of great perfection, with hazard of liberty, and lyfe, forſaking of Countrey, kinsfolkes, friends <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will not ſtand with him, whether Paſtours in Catholicke Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, who are properly Ordinaryes, will be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, that he preferre the Seminary Prieſts Calling, before theyrs, whereby they are alſo obliged to hazard their Iſues for their ſheepe, and with greater immobility, then Seminary Prieſts are. This I will ſay, that his aſſertion deſtroyeth thoſe groundes wherby <hi>n. 42.</hi> he end eauoureth to preferre the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Secular Curates, before thoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, who by their Inſtitute performe the functions of Paſtours, by Preaching, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtring Sacraments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which there he allead geth, in fauour of Curates, agaynſt Religious men, do in the very ſame manner vrge agaynſt Seminary Prieſts, all being reduced to this, that Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes do thoſe functions by Ordinary right &amp; office, Religious by Commiſſion, Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Priuiledges, as likewiſe Seminary
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16320:42"/>Prieſts do: and therfore he muſt eyther pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thoſe Religious, or not preferre Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſts before Curates. Beſydes, if Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary Prieſts ought to be preferred before Curates, becauſe they dayly hazard their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and life; Curates will ſay, that this reaſon proueth too much, namely, that the Seminary Prieſts calling is not only the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt vnder the Biſhop, but alſo, that it is higher then the calling of thoſe Biſhops, who do not dayly hazard their liberty and lyfe, that is to ſay, of moſt part of Biſhops. Laſtly, if once the <hi>Replyer</hi> grant, that the Ordinary Paſtorſhip of Curates, may be prepondera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to which Seminary Prieſts expoſe themſelues, he openeth an eaſy way, to defend, that Religious Prieſts by reaſon of their ſtate, fitneſſe to help their neighbour <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be preferred before Curats, although theſe be ordinaryes, and Religious be not, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if thoſe Religious, be alſo ordayned to help their neighbour. And heere I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not omit to note ſome ſtrang ſpeaches of the <hi>Replyer,</hi> who <hi>n. 42.</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe Religious who by their Inſtitute do many functions of Paſtours, as preaching, miniſtring of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſayth, That in Regulars this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſory, in Paſtours principall; in Regulars it is voluntary, in Paſtours neceſſary <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For who euer heard that it is acceſſory, or volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to a Religious man, to performe thoſe things, to which he is obliged by his very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute?</p>
            <p n="15">15. All that he hath agaynſt the <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> about the diſtinction of leauing all thinges
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16320:43"/>in preparation of mynd, and actuall leauing all things, goeth vpon a ſuppoſition, as if <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Smith</hi> had denyed that diſtinction, which he neuer did; and therfore in vayne he alleadgeth Authors in proofe of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction agaynſt the <hi>Diſcuſsour,</hi> who only ſayd, and proued, that euen in preparation of mynd to leaue all things, Religious excell ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; &amp; that the leauing of all things added a great perfection to the preparation of mynd, it being an Heroicall, and very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious act; ſo much, that <hi>S. Thomas 1. part. q. 43. art. 6.</hi> doubted not to teach, that the Holy Ghoſt is ſent in a particular manner, when one forſaketh all that he poſſeſſed. Lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all that the <hi>Replyer</hi> bringeth to proue, that Counſels are iuſtruments to Perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe, for which he needleſſy alledgeth Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; is anſwered out of the <hi>Diſcuſſion,</hi> where we may gather, that a thing may be ſayd to belong to Perfection only inſtrumentally, or eſſentially, as Charity is; or laſtly inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily and ſecondarily, as S. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith the Couſels are, which is more then only inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, as the habits of vertues diſtinct fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Charity, are Perfection ſecondarily, but not only inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally; which the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicateth <hi>n.</hi> 23. What <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> alledged out of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> that Charity conſiſteth ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily in the loue of our neighbour, was only to ſhew, that there is differece betwixt ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, and only inſtrumentally; becauſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> Charity conſiſteth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily in the loue of our neighbour; but no man will ſay, that Charity conſiſteth in the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16320:43"/>loue of our Neyghbour inſtrumentally; and that therfore <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſayd not well, that Perfection conſiſteth in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally; whereas <hi>S. Thomas</hi> had ſayd, that Perfection conſiſteth in the Counſels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally, and ſecondarily. But the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſsour</hi> neuer intended, to make a parity in all reſpects, betweene the loue of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the Euangelicall Counſels. And ſo all is anſwered, that he hath <hi>n. 65.</hi> Finally that which <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> chiefly found fault with in <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> was not the diſtinctions of preparation of mynd, and actuall leauing all things, or a perfection eſſentially, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally; but his indiſtinct, ambiguous, and obſcure manner of propoſing, &amp; apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, as in expreſſe wordes may be ſeene in the <hi>Diſcuſſion n. 23.24.25.</hi> And indeed <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Smith</hi> did of purpoſe vſe, that circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, becauſe he knew well, that thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctions were good, being rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and fitly applyed. I deſire the Reader to peruſe the place alleadged in the <hi>Diſcuſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. To proue that the Apoſtles were not Religious, he doth his beſt endeauour, and in fyne <hi>Sarmiento</hi> alone is the man, by him alleadged, who doth indeed deny, that the Apoſtles were Religious. But ſeeing that, as <hi>Nicholas Smith q.</hi> 7. <hi>n.</hi> 7. did wiſh, a Learned Penne hath ſince the printing of this <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion</hi> hand led this matter, ſo fully, as more cannot be deſired, I referre the Reader to that Treatiſe, namely the <hi>Apology for &amp;c.</hi> which in my Preface I mentioned, where he ſhall fynd this poynt handled, <hi>Cap. 7.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="question">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:16320:44"/>
            <head>THE VI. QVESTION. <hi>Whether Religious, as Religions, be of the Hierarchy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE whole diſcourſe of the <hi>Replyer,</hi> in this queſtion, is anſwered by only ſetting downe the ſtate of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion aright, as the <hi>Diſcuſſour</hi> hath done <hi>n. 8.</hi> &amp; the <hi>Qualificator Sect.</hi> 5. where all is anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is brought by the <hi>Inquiſitor;</hi> &amp; the <hi>Replyer</hi> hath no more in effect then he. For both of them will needs haue the Queſtion to be; whether Religious, as Religious be of the Hierarchy, as Hierarchs, Princes, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours therof, which is to make the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchicall body of Gods church conſiſt only of Heades: wheras the Queſtion is; Whether properly, ſimply, and abiolutly, Regulars, as Regulars, be not of the Hierarchy; as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt they are more then Secular, as Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, who, as ſuch, are inferiour to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as Religious. Not only amongſt the Hierarchs, but amongſt thoſe alſo, who are gouerned, there is diuerſity of degrees, and all belong to the Hie rarchy, more, or leſſe, according to the perfection of their ſtate, &amp; calling, which in Regulars, is very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable among diuers degrees of Perſons in Gods Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He endeauoureth at large to proue, out of <hi>S. Denis,</hi> That none are of the Hierarchy, except Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, which is true in that particular ſenſe, which <hi>S. Denis</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:16320:44"/>intendeth. But the <hi>Replyer</hi> muſt anſwere his owne argument, &amp; confeſſe, that in another ſenſe, others beſides thoſe three mentioned, are of the Hierarchy. For <hi>M. Doctour Chap. 8.</hi> teacheth, that all in <hi>leſſer Orders,</hi> as <hi>Acolyts &amp;c.</hi> are of the Hierarchy, and the <hi>Replyern. 43.</hi> endeauoureth to proue, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> placeth Cardinals in the Hierarchy. Beſides, as I haue ſayd, ſome Religious, by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, muſt illuminate others, &amp; be Prieſts; <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſuch, euen as Religious, belong to the Hierarchy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the <hi>Replyer</hi> will exclude all from the Hierarchy, except Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, then <hi>M. Doctour Chap. 8. n. 8.</hi> doth by the ſacred Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> pronounce h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m accurſed. Thus he writeth: <hi>Certayne it is, that the Orders of Bishops, Prieſts, Deacons, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons are of the diuine Institution. Wherfore the Councel of</hi> Trent <hi>thus pronounceth (Seſſ. 23. can. 6.)</hi> Si quis dixerit &amp;c. <hi>If any one shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay, that there is not in the Church a Hierarchy, instituted by the diuine Ordinance, which conſisteth of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Priests, and Ministers, let him be accurſed. In which wordes the Councell defyning, that there is a Hierarchy instituted by the diuine ordinance, &amp; which conſiſteth of Bishops, Priests, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters in the plural number, muſt needs vnderstand at least Deacons, and Subdeacons. So that this Hierarchy of Order, at least in reſpect of Bishops, Priests, Deacons, and Subdeacons is instituted by Chriſt.</hi> Thus far <hi>M. Doctour.</hi> Wherfore to free your ſelfe from a Curſe, and <hi>S. Denis</hi> from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in <hi>M. Doctours</hi> opinion, you muſt grant, that you haue not rightly alleadged <hi>S. Denis,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:16320:45"/>to proue, that only Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, are of the Hierarchy, in ſuch manner that all other muſt be excluded. For <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour</hi> hath tould you, as a matter of Faith, that Subdeacons alſo are of the Hierarchy, &amp; that by diuine Inſtitution. You muſt then explicate <hi>S. Denis,</hi> that he nameth Biſhops, Prieſts, &amp; Deacons, not to exclude all other, but becauſe theſe are the higheſt Orders in the Chutch, and ſo Religious may be of the Hierarchy, notwithſtanding what you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge out of <hi>S. Denis,</hi> who doth expreſly place the order of Monkes in the Hierarchy <hi>Cap. 6. tit. Contemplatio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Likewiſe, when the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> defineth, as a matter of Faith, that by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Ordinace, there is in the Church a Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, which conſiſteth of Biſhops, Prieſts. and Miniſters, which ſome moderne Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques denyed, it only followeth, that ſuch are certaynly of the Hierarchy, but not that they only are, as many Deuines hold leſſer Orders not to be of the diuine Inſtitution: and yet <hi>M. Doctour</hi> teacheth that all in leſſer Orders, are of the Hierarchy, and no man will affirme, that the ſacred Councell inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to condemne as Hereticques, thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, who teach that the Leſſer Orders are not of diuine inſtitution: or that, according to the Councell, it is an Hereſy to ſay, that Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inals, Vicar-Generals, Archdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who are not of the diuine Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea are not neceſſarily Biſhops, Prieſts, Deacons, or Subdeacons, can belong to the Hierarchy. And therfore the <hi>Replyer</hi> had no reaſon to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16320:45"/>blame <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> ſo ſeuerely, as he doth <hi>n. 11.</hi> for ſaying, that it were raſhneſſe to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the Councell intended, to define as a matter of Fayth, that vnder the name of Hierarchy could be comprehended only Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At length the <hi>Replyer n. 13.</hi> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to extend <hi>S. Denis</hi> his doctrine, and to bring in Subdeacons, and other inferiour Orders, as likwiſe he muſt fynd meanes to bring in Cardinals, Archdeacons, Vicar-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; finally giue ſome place to poore Religious men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thus his reaſons from <hi>n. 21.</hi> to <hi>26.</hi> fall of themſelues, as only prouing that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as Religious, preciſely, are not Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or Illuminators in the Hierarchy, but not, that they are not of it properly, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, or not more then Secular, formally as Secular. And if they be Prieſts, &amp; Paſtours, they are as much of the Hierarchy, in euery reſpect, as Secular Prieſts, and Paſtours.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is ſtrang to ſee how <hi>n. 28.</hi> he trifleth, as if <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> had euer denyed, that the Hierarchy comprehendeth both Order, and Iuriſdiction. Wheras he expreſly affirmeth it <hi>n. 3.</hi> and thence inferreth, that the word Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy hath a latitude.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He doth not <hi>n. 31.</hi> ſufficiently free <hi>M. Doctour</hi> from the <hi>Diſcuſſours</hi> iuſt complaint, for his ſaying, That <hi>S. Bernard</hi> affirmed the Hierarchy to be perturbed, when Abbots are ſubtracted from the Biſhops Iuriſdiction. For the Saint expreſly approueth Exemptions, &amp; only reprehendeth ſuch as are granted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, or procured vpon ambition, as at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16320:46"/>length the <hi>Replyer</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth; and therfore <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ought not abſolutly to haue alleadged <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> as ſaying, the Church is perturbed, when Abbots are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the Biſhops Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The <hi>Diſcuſsour</hi> neuer taught, Grace, or Charity alone can place one in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hierarchy: For they alone, are not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to make one a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the Church militant. But he taught, that an external Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſtate of Lyfe, ordayned to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Grace, and Charity, is ſufficient to place the Profeſſours thereof in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hierarchy, in that degree, wherin according to their ranke, they excell others not in that degree, wherin ſome particular Religious man, may chance to excell ſome Biſhop, in grace, and Charity, becauſe that is accidentall to their ſtates: as likwiſe ſome lay man, or woman, may exceed ſome Religious man, in perfection of the loue of God. And by this is anſwered, what he hath <hi>n. 33.</hi> about <hi>Nauclerus,</hi> who cannot be denyed, to haue placed Religious men in the Hierarchy, in a high degree, not only accidentally, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome particular Religious mens Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but <hi>per ſe loquendo,</hi> &amp; by reaſon of their ſtate. Alſo, out of what we haue ſayd, is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily anſwered the obiection he bringeth <hi>n. 42.</hi> againſt the argument, which <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> made <hi>n.</hi> 9. where he proueth; That if ſome men by Grace, may, according to S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> be aſſumed to the Order of Angels, in the Celeſtiall Hierarchy; an externall ſtate of life affoarding moſt effectuall meanes, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16320:46"/>of grace in this lyfe, may well place men on earth, in the Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy. But <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> neuer dreamed, that men by grace become indeed Angels, Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. All that he hath <hi>n. 34. 35.</hi> about the tranſlation of S. <hi>Denis</hi> his definition of a Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, is anſwered in the <hi>Admonition to the Reader,</hi> adioyned to the <hi>Qualification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> to proue that one may be of the Hierarchy, although by office he do not illuminate, or perfect others, inſtanceth in the loweſt Angell, who is not to illuminate any other, and yet cannot be excluded from the Celeſtiall Hierarchy. What doth the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> anſwere? Nothing in effect, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying, that the loweſt Angell, or Order of Angels, are abſolutly of the Celeſtiall Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, but only in a certayne ſenſe, which indeed he muſt needes affirme, by the ſame reaſons for which he denyeth Religious to be of the Hierarchy, becauſe their office is not to illuminate, or perfect others. But this doctrine is a thing vnheard of amongſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, who with the holy Fathers teach, that there are nine Orders of Angels, compriſed in three Hierarchies: but now the <hi>Replyer</hi> will haue one Order of Angels, belonging to no Hierarchy. If he put Angels out of the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall, Religious men haue, I confeſſe, leſſe reaſon to wonder, or take it ill, if he exclude them from the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchy.</p>
            <p n="11">11. What he ſayth <hi>n. 43. 44.</hi> to wit, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> denyed not Cardinalls to be of the Hierarchy, he will not be able to mantayne,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16320:47"/>without granting, that to be of the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, neyther Iuriſdiction, nor Order is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. For although Cardinalls may be in Orders, and actually haue Iuriſdiction ouer their titles, yet their Iuriſdiction, as <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour Chap. 10. n. 19.</hi> ſayth out of <hi>Bedarmine,</hi> is but like to the Iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Pariſh Prieſt in his Pariſh; &amp; that Iuriſdiction is acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to the office of Cardinall, as Cardinall, which reſpecteth the common good of the vniuerſall Church, and yet euen as Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, they haue a moſt eminent place in the Hierarchy, next to the Pope. If once it be graunted, that neyther Order nor Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is required, to place one in the Hierarchy, then Religious men, whoſe ſtate is in the Church of God much reſpected, yea beſides whome, none except Biſhops, are in ſtate of Perfection, according to <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> may be, &amp; are of the Hierarchy in a very perfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, In a word. if Cardinalls be not of the Hierarchy, <hi>M. Doctour</hi> had not byn much wronged, although <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> had ſayd, that by his Principles they muſt be excluded from it: and yet for this cauſe the <hi>Replyer n. 43.</hi> is much offended with the <hi>Diſcuſſour.</hi> If they be of the Hierarchy, then not only Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, are of the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, as the <hi>Replyer</hi> hath much laboured to proue out of <hi>S. Denis:</hi> and by that labour, hath only put himſelfe vpon an ineuitable neceſſity, to anſwere the arguments he made for excluding Religious men.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Neuertheleſſe, if to make one of the Hierarchy, it be neceſſary that he illuminate,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16320:47"/>&amp; perfect others; Religious, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Religious, cannot be excluded: becauſe for Regular ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruances, they illuminate one another, and in that, do not neceſſarily depend, but are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xempt from Biſhops, as the King or Mayſter of a houſe dependeth not on the Biſhop, for the meere temporall adminiſtration of his Kingdome, or family. And ſo that part of the Hierarchy, which by <hi>S. Gregory Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen orat. in laudem Baſil.</hi> is ſtyled <hi>Eccleſiae pars ſelectior &amp; ſapientior,</hi> the more wiſe &amp; choice part of the Church, hath its proper Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, touching noble actions, and a ſtate of lyfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which for the perfection of it, was by our B. Sauiour counſelled not commanded, as being aboue the reach of Ordinary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, according to that of <hi>Matt. 19. Qui potest capere, capiat.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="question">
            <head>THE VII. QVESTION. <hi>Whether by the precedent Questions, we haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently anſwered</hi> M. Doctours <hi>Treatiſe, for ſuch poynts, as eyther deſerued Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, or required explication.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THIS Queſtion was propoſed by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Smith,</hi> not to boaſt of what he had donne, in the precedent Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, as the <hi>Replyer pag. 20. n. 31.</hi> is pleaſed to inſinuate, but to the end the Reader might know, where to fynd anſwere to any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in <hi>M. Doctours</hi> booke, which the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſour</hi> did not anſwere Chapter for Chapter, and number for number.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Replyer n. 3.</hi> writeth, that to him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16320:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſeemeth a ſtrange ſpeach, &amp; litle edifying, to ſay, as <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſayth, that he neuer heard, that the Church muſt be gouerned by the Secular Cleargy. <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> did indeed wonder, to heare <hi>M. Doctour</hi> ſay in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle <hi>n. 12.</hi> that Secular Prieſts, are by the diuine Inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gouernours of the church. <hi>The Church</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>must be gouerned by the Secular Cleargy. May not Bishops, and other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours in Gods Church be Religious men? How then is it a diuine Institution, that the Church must be gouerned by the Secular Cleargy?</hi> Thus the <hi>Diſcuſſour.</hi> And what can be more true? For if by diuine Inſtitution, the gouernment of the Church belong to the Secular Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, then is it a breach of the diuine law, to aſſume Religious men to be Biſhops, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, which is to condemne the dayly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Gods Church. The <hi>Replyer</hi> bringeth not one reaſon to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute what <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſayd, ſaue only, that the Church, for the moſt part, is gouerned by the Secular Cleargy, which is farre from prouing, that it is a <hi>diuine Justitution, that the Church be gouerned by the Secular Cleargy;</hi> as it cannot be proued, that Preaching, for example, or conuerting of Infidels, by diuine Inſtitution belonges to the Regular Clergy, becauſe they preach at home to faithfull people, and are ſent to remote Countreys for the Conuerſion of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, more then Secular Prieſts. <hi>Snarez</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Replyer n. 5.</hi> neuer ſayd, that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Paſtours, gouerne by Delegation, or Priuiledge or that it is againſt the diuine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Religious me be made Paſtours.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16320:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. From his <hi>n.</hi> 10. to <hi>15.</hi> he goeth about to proue, that my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> is Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, after an extraordinary manner, by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, eaſy to be anſwered, if it were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the defence of <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> as it is not; and therfore I referre the Reader, to the anſwere of the Regulars, to my Lord of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedons</hi> letter. For the <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Nicolas Smith,</hi> it is inough, to take what the <hi>Repiyer</hi> yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, to wit, that my Lord is not Ordinary, in an Ordinary manner, as <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by the definition of an Ordinary, giuen by <hi>M. Doctour.</hi> For this grant ſuppoſed, I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue thus: The diuine Inſtitution, that in the whole Church, and (as <hi>M. Doctour</hi> would thence inferre) in euery notable part therof, there ſhould be Biſhops, is eyther fulfilled in <hi>England,</hi> by placing there my Lord of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> or not. If it be fulfilled, then the Pope might in the whole Church place only Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaryes in an extraordinary manner, by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, or Commiſſion, which no Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke can grant. If it be not fulfilled in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Pope is yet obliged to giue vs a Biſhop, Ordinary in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary manner, which I belieue he will not admit, and therfore he muſt finally yield to the <hi>Diſcuſſour;</hi> That there is no diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, to haue a Biſhop in <hi>England,</hi> but all muſt be left to the ſupreme Paſtours diſcretion, whether it be beſt for vs to be gouerned by a Biſhop, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Diſcuſſour n. 5.</hi> concerning my Lord of <hi>Chalcedons</hi> maintenance, vttered nothing vpon his owne opinion, but truly related,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16320:49"/>what others did, and do ſay, himſelfe abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to intermeddle in that matter: yet the <hi>Replyers</hi> argument <hi>n. 17.</hi> rather proueth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Catholicks are not obliged to mantayne my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> if without his Lordſhip they can be ſufficiently prouided, of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall helpes, by Prieſts, Secular or Regular; becauſe by the law of Nature, they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged only to prouide themſelues, of meanes to atrayne ſaluation. Whether or no, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes can be ſufficiently prouided for, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Lord of <hi>Chalcedon; Nicolas Smith</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſputed, nor did he euer giue the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation, that it were better not to haue a Biſhop in <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> wholly referring that point, to the determination of his Holines: and the <hi>Replyer</hi> is much to blame, for his taxing the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> as oppoſing the comming of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop into <hi>England.</hi> Thoſe Houſes which the <hi>Replyer n. 18.</hi> tearmeth <hi>stately,</hi> and turneth from the ſingular, to the plurall number, are knowne by thoſe, who haue beſt reaſon to know it, not to haue put Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes to charges; and although they had, yet it is knowne, that all was for their ſeruice, to prepare ſuch as might, in due tyme, employ their labours, and lyfe, in help of England.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Replyer</hi> hath no reaſon, to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with the <hi>Diſcuſſour,</hi> for ſaying, that <hi>M. Doctour</hi> was miſtaken, while he put <hi>Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Siluerius,</hi> and <hi>Martinus</hi> to haue ſuffered martyrdome before <hi>Constantines</hi> tyme. For his marginall note hath <hi>(27. Popes martyrs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tyme of Constantine)</hi> amongſt which 27. thoſe three were placed. Yea <hi>M. Doctour</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:16320:49"/>produceth them to proue, that Popes were created, euen in tyme of Perſecution, when the Creation of Popes, or Biſhops was op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; for which purpoſe, the example of thoſe three Popes, could not ſerue, vnleſſe he had conceaued, that they were before <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine,</hi> for otherwiſe he could not imagine, but that they ſuffered in tyme of Chriſtian Emperours, as de <hi>facto</hi> thoſe three Popes did, when the creation of Popes, was not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly oppoſed. The reaſons alleadged by the <hi>Replyer,</hi> only proue, that if <hi>M. Doctour</hi> miſtooke, he had no reaſon for it: yet to do the <hi>Replyer</hi> a fauour, I will be content with him, to caſt the errour vpon one, whome he ſayth <hi>M. Doctour</hi> truſted, in making the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall notes, vpon condition that he giue me leaue to ſay, that thoſe three Popes, who dyed not before <hi>Constantine,</hi> made not to the purpoſe, for which they were by <hi>M. Doctour</hi> alleadged. And becauſe I would not wrong him, who made the marginall notes, I muſt in his behalfe ſay, that he had but reaſon, to make the note as he did, conſidering <hi>M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> drift, &amp; manner of expreſſing himſelfe. It is a wonder that in this very place, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyer</hi> would helpe himſelfe with a marginall note, and excuſe <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> becauſe he ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Bozius</hi> in the margent, which (ſayth he) <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> ſhould haue mentioned. But <hi>Bozius</hi> neuer ſaid, that thoſe three Popes were before <hi>Constantine,</hi> and therfore yieldeth no excuſe for <hi>M. Doctour,</hi> nor had <hi>Nicolas Smith</hi> any obligation to mention him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Replyer n. 27.</hi> endeth his booke
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16320:50"/>with theſe wordes. <hi>He that findes himſelfe able to ouercome the temptations of the world, and with the grace of God, hath Confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce not only to worke his owne ſaluation, but alſo the ſaluation of many others; let him, if he like that state, take vpon him an Apostolicall, Priestly courſe of life; Prieſts being to liue in the midst of the difficultyes of the world, by reaſon of their Preaching, Teaching, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministring Sacraments. Jf he otherwiſe be weake, feeble, &amp; is hardly able to paſse through thoſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; allurements with ſafety of his own ſoule, let him hasten to ſome Religious courſe of lyfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to his force, and liking: and if he hath not thoſe talents, which are required in Priests, and that he cannot brooke the auſterity of Religion, let him endeauour to ſerue God in the world.</hi> Thus he declaring, what meane conceit he hath of Religious perfection. And I pray God, the like apprehenſion, haue not taken deepe roote, in too many now a dayes. Your diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of diuers ſortes of perſons, is not ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate. For, beſides thoſe whome you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is a fourth kind of perſons, who haue confidence, by Gods grace, to ſaue their ſoules in the world, and yet for attayning of Perfection, &amp; greater vnion with their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, are not content, only to keep Gods Commandements in the world, but alſo are inflamed with a deſire, to obſerue the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Counſels in a Religious ſtate: &amp; ſome of thoſe, beſydes the perfection of their owne ſoule, are further called, euen in a Religious ſtate, to procure the ſaluation, and perfection of their neyghbour, eyther by their proper Inſtitute, or by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand of their Superiours.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16320:50"/>If your conceite were ſolid, whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldeth a Religious man, might poynt at him, and ſay: This was a weake, and feeble perſon, &amp; hardly able to paſſe in the world, with the ſafety of his owne ſoule. A raſh, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, &amp;, I may ſay, vnchriſtian cenſure. S. <hi>Thomas 2.2. q. 189. ar. 1.</hi> of purpoſe teacheth, that not only perſons, already habituated in obſeruation of the commandements, but all ſinners may enter into Religion; thoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in perfection, theſe to auoyde ſinne. This Saint then held it for certayne, that Religion is not only for thoſe, who are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, &amp; feeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, &amp; hardly able to paſſe through the temptations of the world, with the ſafety of their ſoule, but much more, for ſuch as are already grounded in vertue, and by that meanes, better diſpoſed to attayne Religious perfection. Certainly, the Angelicall <hi>Doctour</hi> would haue made vs an Exhortation, farre different from yours, and would haue ſayd: If any feare his owne frailty in the world, and otherwiſe haue talents for Religion, let him vndertake that ſtate. Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a ſtate of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. If any with the keeping of the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, deſire to ioyne the obſeruation of the Euangelicall Counſels, let him haſten to Religion. Religion is a courſe of lyfe, for its height, counſelled, not commanded. If any already good, deſire to be perfect, let him fly to Religion. Religion is a ſchoole of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as our B. Sauiour <hi>Matth. 19.</hi> to one that had all ready kept the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, ſayd: <hi>Jf thou wilt be perfect go ſell the things that thou haſt. &amp;c.</hi> If any togeather with his owne Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16320:51"/>thirſt after the ſaluation, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of others; with great merit, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to himſelfe, let him imbrace a Religious courſe. Religion not only perfecteth a mans ſelfe, but alſo enableth him to help others, with leſſe danger to his owne ſoule. God grant we were as carefull to correſpond to our Vocation, as we are certayne the Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it ſelfe is perfect; of which S. <hi>Bernard (l. de praecept &amp; diſpo.)</hi> was not afrayd to ſay, <hi>Praeeminet vniuerſis vitae humanae gencribus:</hi> It hath a preheminency before all kindes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane lyfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>THE CONCLVSION.</head>
            <p>One ſaith, it is the worſt property of warre that proſperous ſucceſſes are imputed to all, misfortunes to ſome one. <hi>(Tacit. in vita A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gric.)</hi> Contrarywiſe in this Pen-Combat, I wiſh, that whatſoeuer is amiſſe, may fall only vpon my ſelfe. If any thing yield ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, I hartily deſire, it may wholy redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the honour of Epiſcopall Dignity, to the commendation of a Religious ſtate, to peace amongſt our ſelues, and, aboue all, to the Eternall Glory of the moſt B. Trinity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:16320:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAg. 37. lin. 7. euery <hi>corrige</hi> very.</item>
               <item>Pag. 52. lin. 1. thero <hi>corrige</hi> therof.</item>
               <item>Pag. 53. lin. 1. -mily <hi>corrige</hi> -mity.</item>
               <item>Pag. 66. lin. vlt. Chrity <hi>corrige</hi> Charity.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
